<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A door of salvation opened unto all men: or a short treatise, discovering that all man-kinde as they are considered under the fall of Adam, have an equal and a like respect with almighty God, and that by Jesus Christ he hath prepared eternal salvation for all, and afforded unto all, means sufficient to bring them thereunto. In which also, sundry objections, grounds of reason, and texts of scripture, for the contrary opinion are alleadged and answered. / By R.B.</title>
            <author>R. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 202 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76313</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B166</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1166_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208726</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867650</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867650</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119970</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76313)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119970)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 166:E1166[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A door of salvation opened unto all men: or a short treatise, discovering that all man-kinde as they are considered under the fall of Adam, have an equal and a like respect with almighty God, and that by Jesus Christ he hath prepared eternal salvation for all, and afforded unto all, means sufficient to bring them thereunto. In which also, sundry objections, grounds of reason, and texts of scripture, for the contrary opinion are alleadged and answered. / By R.B.</title>
                  <author>R. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 108, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Wil. Larnar, and are to be sold at the sign of the Blackmore near Bishops-gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Marsh. 30".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Salvation --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119970:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DOOR OF SALVATION OPENED Unto all Men: <hi>OR</hi> A SHORT TREATISE, <hi>Diſcovering</hi> That all man-kinde as they are conſidered under the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> have an equal and a like reſpect with Almighty God, and that by Jeſus Chriſt he hath prepared eternal Salvation for All, and afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto All, means ſufficient to bring them thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In which alſo,</hi> Sundry Objections, Grounds of Reaſon, and Texts of Scripture, for the contrary Opinion are alleadged and anſwered.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezek. 18.4.</hi>
               </bibl> Behold all ſouls are mine, as the ſoul of the father, ſo alſo the ſoul of the ſonne is mine: the ſoul that ſinneth it ſhall die.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Wil. Larnar,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſign of the <hi>Blackmore</hi> near <hi>Biſhops-gate,</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119970:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119970:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO The Impartial READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S concerning what I here preſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, I am nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant of my ſwerving therein from the common Opinions of the Times, nor yet inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the many cenſures I
<pb facs="tcp:119970:3"/>
ſhall incurre from ſome by reaſon thereof; But <hi>He that obſerveth the winde, ſhall not ſowe: and he that regardeth the clouds, ſhall not reap. (Eccleſ.</hi> 11.4.) The ſcope of Scriptures, and light of reaſon is the ground of my belief, and my onely rule in this: From which I have not conſciouſly erred in any thing contained therein. Notwithſtanding conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mine own, with the common frailty of all men
<pb facs="tcp:119970:3"/>
now living, I crave not thy acceptance in any thing more, than what after a diligent peruſall, with a free and impartiall exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination upon the fore-ſaid Grounds, ſhall appear war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable unto thee. All which I humbly deſire thee, as well for thine own happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (depending thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) as for the good and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of others, thankfully and gladly to receive in the love thereof, faithfully to
<pb facs="tcp:119970:4"/>
practice, and induſtriouſly to promote in thy whole Converſation: And ſo refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thee to the Diſcourſe it ſelf, and the Grace of God diſcovered therein, I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in all Chriſtian duty <hi>R. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:119970:4"/>
            <head>A TABLE Directing to ſome of the moſt principal Heads contained in this TREATISE.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>ALL men as they are conſidered in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> have a like esteem and reſpect with God, <hi>page 5, 7, 8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> made mutable, and why, <hi>pag. 33.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Adams</hi> first offence incurred not the damnation of hell, <hi>58.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:119970:5"/>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Children</hi> not dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, nor liable to the damnation of hell by birth, <hi>pag. 57, 58.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> was ſent into the world to be a Saviour for all men, <hi>pag. 16, 17, 18, 19.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath redeemed all men from death brought upon them by <hi>Adams</hi> diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, <hi>13, 32, 58, 92.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath prepared and opened a way to eternal life for all men, <hi>pag. 13, 14, 47, 48.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When the <hi>Covenant</hi> of Grace was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, <hi>p. 92, 93.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That it is extended unto all men, <hi>p. 90.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How works are required thereby to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, <hi>p. 79, 80.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Wherein it is moſt properly distinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, from the <hi>Covenant</hi> of works, <hi>p. 83, 84, 85, 86, 87.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:119970:5"/>And in what reſpects it is to be esteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>Covenant</hi> of Grace, <hi>p. 87, 88, 89.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>None <hi>elected</hi> to Salvation as they are conſidered in the eſtate of diſobedience, <hi>p. 72, 73, 80.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>Wherein <hi>Faith</hi> conſisteth, <hi>p. 51.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How it is begotten in men, <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That none are unavoidably enforced thereunto, <hi>p. 5, 6, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That if <hi>Faith</hi> were enforced none could be justified by it, <hi>p. 44, 45, 46, 54, 55, 56.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In what reſpect it is ſaid to be the gift of God, <hi>p. 50, 51, 52, 53, 54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That men may poſſibly fall away from it, <hi>p. 11, 12, 14, 101, 102, 103, 104.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:119970:6"/>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>That God requireth not more of any men to their Salvation, then what by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of the means they may perform <hi>p. 22, 23, 24, 27, 36, 37, 42, 43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>God</hi> neither hardeneth the hearts, blindeth the eyes, nor worketh wickednes in any men. <hi>p. 31, 32.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>That all vertue and vice proceedeth from the hearts of men, <hi>p. 44, 45, 54, 55, 56.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That every mans judgement at the last day ſhall be according to the things only that were freely choſen and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein, <hi>ibid</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:119970:6"/>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>In what reſpect it is ſaid, That the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall <hi>man</hi> perceiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, <hi>p. 57, 58, 59, 60, 61, 62, 63, 64, 65, 66.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How men are taught of God, and drawn unto Jeſus Christ, <hi>p. 66, 67, 68, 69.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How it is wrought in them to will and to do, <hi>&amp;c. p. 69, 70, 71.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How it is given unto them to repent, <hi>p. 77, 78, 79.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>To believe in Chriſt, and to ſuffer for his ſake, <hi>p. 76, 77.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And how God putteth his Laws into the mindes of men, <hi>p. 95. to the end of the Chapter.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>That no man can be <hi>ſaved</hi> without the grace of God, nor no man be <hi>ſaved</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:119970:7"/>
without his obedience unto it. <hi>p. 15, 16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In what nature <hi>Salvation</hi> is given by God unto men, <hi>p. 15, 16, 49, 50.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>And what in generall is required of all men for the obtaining thereof, <hi>p. 55, 56, 81, 82.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:119970:7"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THrough want of opportunity to attend the Preſſe, ſeveral eſcapes have been made in the Printing hereof (and ſome of them ſuch as pervert the very ſence of the place where they are committed) moſt of which (in the two firſt ſheets) I thought good (more eſpecially) to give thee notice of, to the end that thou mighteſt correct them, as well as any other, which thou ſhalt obſerve in the reading of the whole.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 4. lin. 4. for <hi>from the enjoyment,</hi> read <hi>and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment.</hi> p. 18. l. 28. for <hi>other,</hi> r. <hi>greater.</hi> p. 19. l. 18. for <hi>made in under,</hi> r. <hi>made in him under.</hi> p. 20. l. 3. for <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> r. <hi>denieth.</hi> p. 24. l. 5. for <hi>tendreth,</hi> r. <hi>rendreth.</hi> p. 27. l. 19. for <hi>we,</hi> r. <hi>men.</hi> p. 27. l. 22. for <hi>inveterable,</hi> r. <hi>inveterate.</hi> p. 30. l. 5. for <hi>magnified,</hi> r. <hi>imagined.</hi> p. 38. l. 14. for <hi>oppoſe,</hi> r. <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth.</hi> p. 62. l. 31. add <hi>which.</hi> p. 67. l. 1. for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> r. <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im.</hi> p. 69. l. 32. for <hi>and happines,</hi> r. <hi>and of obtaining happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</hi> p. 74. l. 11. for <hi>apprehended,</hi> r. <hi>applied.</hi> p. 80. l. 24. for <hi>with</hi> r. <hi>by.</hi> p. 95. l. 23. for <hi>he,</hi> r. <hi>I.</hi> p. 99. l. 24. dele <hi>from this text.</hi> p. 100. l. 6. add <hi>and.</hi> p. 105. l. 1. for <hi>this,</hi> r. <hi>his.</hi> Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript, p. 2. l. 12. for <hi>internity,</hi> r. <hi>infirmity.</hi> ibid. p. l. 19. for <hi>offered,</hi> r. <hi>afforded.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119970:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119970:8"/>
            <head>A DOORE OF SALVATION OPENED UNTO AL MEN.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>The Introduction.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as man-kinde commeth not into this. World alwaies to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue therein, but is appointed after a ſhort ſpace to leave the ſame, and returne to corruption: And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as we are abundantly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by God in the Scriptures of our Reſtauration from thence to an eſtate of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality in the World that is to come; wherein eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhall receive according to his deeds done in this life, and are thereupon often required to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their latter end, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.20. (to wit) death and Iudgement to come; to the intent that from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration thereof, they may be lead ſo to paſſe the time of their being here in feare, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. that it may go well with them at that day: It having other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119970:9"/>
been (according to the ſaying of Chriſt, though here they had gained the Dominion of the whole World) good for them that they had never been born, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.26. In which regard, there cannot poſſibly be any thing of greater concernment unto men, than to be informed what it is that God requireth of them in this World to the aforeſaid end, and how they may be inabled to the doing thereof; becauſe that what a man knoweth not, or knoweth not how to performe, he can in no wiſe diſpoſe or apply himſelfe to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof.</p>
               <p>And yet there is not any thing wherein moſt men are more wanting, than in this ſo neceſſary <hi>knowledge,</hi> to the great diſquietneſſe and perplexity of their mindes all their dayes, apprehending themſelves in the greateſt danger, and not underſtanding how or by what meanes they may avoid the ſame; which miſery (as may juſtly be ſuppoſed) happeneth unto them chiefly by reaſon of their dependance for information in the things of this nature upon thoſe perſons only, who unduely ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate unto themſelves to be the infallible teachers of the ignorant, and diſpenſers of the Oracles of God appointed and ſent into the World for all men to aske counſel of, in their Spirituall affaires. Whoſe principals are ſuch as theſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That by <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion all men were brought under the guilt of Temporall, Spirituall, and Eternall death. The firſt conſiſting in the miſeries of this life, and the diſſolution of mans nature in the end thereof. The ſecond in the depravation of the inward man, whereby al men are diſabled from deſcerning ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things, or chooſing the things that are good, or doing any thing pleaſing or acceptable unto God.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119970:9"/>
The third in the deſtruction and perdition of the whole man body and Soul, in hell fire, for ever and ever.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That of man-kinde thus conſidered God in his eternall counſell was pleaſed to chooſe and elect for his ſons and daughters onely ſome few perſons (in compariſon of the whole) whom alſo he decreed to deliver from the fore-ſaid guilt, to call them to the knowledge of himſelfe, to worke in them faith by the effectuall operation of his Spirit, and in the end to give them ſalvation; But decreed to leave all the reſt of man-kinde in that eſtate wherein they were fallen; and that although by the doctrine of the Goſpel, he decreed outwardly to cal them to repent, believe, &amp;c. yet to the intent that they might not eſcape the damnnation of hel, whereunto they were deſign'd (by reaſon of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion) by anſwering his call, &amp; giving obedience thereunto, he further decreed, not onely to deny them the benefit of ſuch meanes which he knew to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to enable them to repent &amp; believe, &amp;c. but he alſo decreed to blinde their eyes, harden their hearts, and to make their ears dul of hearing, leaſt at any time they ſhould ſee with their eyes, hear with their eares, and underſtand with their hearts, &amp; come unto him and be healed, or be converted and have their ſins forgiven them. By which opinions preſſed &amp; received as funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental points in Divinity, men are generally brought to believe, that as the damnation of ſome perſons is altogether impoſſible, God having decreed ſo as of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to worke in them faith, &amp;c. and to bring them to eternall life; ſo on the contray, That the ſalvation of the greateſt part of men is as impoſſible to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, God having denyed unto them all neceſſary meanes for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119970:10"/>The evill of which belief ſo neceſſarily diverting and diſabling all men from the proſecution and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of theſe ends that <hi>God</hi> propoſeth unto them (to wit) an exemption from everlaſting death, and from the enjoyment of eternall life; diſcovereth unto us the errour and falſe-hood of theſe doctrines before reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whereby theſe opinions are begotten and foſtred in them, in regard that it may not be conceived, that God who is truth it ſelf, ſhould require all men to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve his love and favour towards them, manifeſtly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in his frequent, fervent and pathetical exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons unto them in the Scriptures, to hearken unto wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to chooſe his feare, to chooſe life, to worke out their own ſalvation, with feare and trembling, &amp;c. When as in his eternall counſell, for <hi>Adams</hi> offence he hath utterly excluded them from his love, and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverably ſealed them to everlaſting deſtruction.</p>
               <p>And alſo (although it be a moſt certaine truth that God before the World, did elect and chooſe ſome men unto ſalvation, &amp; appoint others to be puniſhed) yet this may juſtly leade us to conceive, that neither the one ſort were elected, nor the other rejected upon the grounds that theſe men pretend, or upon any other than thoſe grounds whereupon God in the Scriptures promiſeth unto men adoption and ſalvation, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth unto them death and reprobation, or thoſe where-upon Chriſt at the laſt day will graciouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſome men with eternall happineſſe, and puniſh others with everlaſting paines; except we will ſet the ſecret and revealed minde of God at an irreconcilable variance; or fancy two mindes in God, oppoſite each unto the other; one whereby he hateth and abhorreth in time, thoſe perſons whom he loved and elected be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119970:10"/>
time; and the other whereby he loveth in time thoſe perſons whom he hated and abhorred before time: which may not be imagined.</p>
               <p>And therefore originally, or as men were conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under the fall of <hi>Adam;</hi> we are to conceive that God maketh no difference, or diſtinction betwixt them, but of his great and abundant grace in Chriſt Jeſus, maketh and openeth unto them all a doore of ſalvation, excluding none, who through their own wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and voluntary diſobedience and contempt of his goodnes, exclude not themſelves; nor ſaving any but thoſe who from a thankfull apprehenſion of his rich mercy revealed unto them in his Word and workes, or both, doe chearfully, and willingly ſubmit themſelves to the obedience of his will, known and underſtood by them.</p>
               <p>For the Probation of which two general heads joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcourſed, &amp; the detection of the contrary opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, exhibited in ſundry objections, reaſons and texts of Scripture, the ſumme of that which followeth is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed; beginning with the firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP I.</hi> That God being no reſpecter of perſons cannot chooſe one man in his diſobedience, and reject another; or enforce one man to believe and not another.</head>
               <p>IF that God ſhould neceſſitate the ſalvation of ſome men and not others, then he ſhould be a reſpecter of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119970:11"/>
perſons contrary to the Scriptures. As will appeare by ſeverall texts thereof. As firſt by <hi>Acts</hi> 10.34. Where <hi>Peter</hi> when he perceived, that God had received unto adoption <hi>Cornelius</hi> a Gentile as well as himſelfe, and others that were Jewes, he thus expreſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Now I perceive of a truth that there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons with God, but in every Nation he that feareth him and worketh righteouſneſſe is eccepted of him: Arguing plainly, that if God ſhould accept of one perſon working righteouſneſſe and not of another as righteous and juſt as he; that therein God ſhould be a reſpecter of perſons, and that the reaſon why God doth not accept of one man working righteouſneſſe, and reject another, is becauſe that he is no reſpecter of perſons.</p>
               <p>Secondly the ſame Apoſtle in 1 <hi>Peter</hi> 1.17. exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Believers to take heed and feare leaſt that they diſobey, and diſpleaſe God, groundeth his exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the impartiality of Gods proceeding towards all men without reſpect of perſons; in which argument there would be no force to diſſwade them from diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, if that God without reſpect of perſons could diſpence with one man in his diſobedience, more than with another.</p>
               <p>Again <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. to the 11. Admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all ſorts of men, Not to deſpiſe the riches of the goodneſſe of God leading them to repentance; but through patience to continue in wel-doing, and not to obey unrighteouſneſſe, for this reaſon. That there is no reſpect of perſons with God. And upon the ſame reaſon <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> chargeth the Judges whom he had appointed to judge the people, To adminiſter righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous judgement, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.7. And likewiſe <hi>Paul,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119970:11"/>
the ſame ground inſtructeth ſervants to ſerve their maſters, not with eye-ſervice: but in ſingleneſſe of heart as to the Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.9. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.25. Clearly evincing, that God being no reſpecter of perſon, hee cannot accept of one man and reject another in the ſame eſtate and condition, (an evill which he reprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.2, 3, 4, 5, 6.) Condemne one man for his offence, and acquit another under the ſame guilt: but to all men in one and the ſame capacity equally and alike, adminiſtreth his mercies and favours, reproofs and puniſhments.</p>
               <p>Which equality of proceedings towards all men is by God himſelfe in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.21, 22, 23, 24, 25. plainly avowed in the words following. <hi>If that the wicked will turne from his ſinnes that he hath committed, and keep all my Statutes, and doe that which is lawfull and right, he ſhall ſurely live, he ſhall not die, all his tranſgreſſions that he hath committed, they ſhall not bee mentioned unto him, in his righteouſneſſe that hee hath done he ſhall live. Have I any pleaſure at all, ſaith the Lord, that the wicked ſhould die, and not that hee ſhould returne from his waies and live. But when the righteous turneth away from his righteouſneſſe, and committeth ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and doth according to all the abominations that the wicked man doth, ſhall he live? All his righteouſneſſe that he hath done ſhall not be mentioned, in his treſpaſſe that he hath treſpaſſed, and in his ſins that he hath ſinned he ſhall die. Yet you ſay the way of the Lord is not equal.</hi> Seeing then that God is no reſpecter of perſons, but diſpenſeth his favour and diſpleaſure in an equall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion and even meaſure unto every man, not prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one before another; it muſt needs thereupon, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that in the eſtate of nature wherein all men are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119970:12"/>
concluded to be alike, every man hath a like eſteeme with him, and receiveth alike from him.</p>
               <p>And although that ſometimes hee affordeth more meanes of Inſtruction unto ſome people in the eſtate of nature, than he doth unto others; as formerly hee did to the Jewes, more than to the Gentiles. Yet if it be conſidered that where he giveth much, hee asketh the more againe, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.48. And that ſuch meanes doth not neceſſarily enforce thoſe perſons to whom it is granted to the love and obedience of the giver thereof; nor that the want of thoſe extraordinary meanes, doth neceſſarily hinder any men from walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing acceptably unto God, but that as the Scriptures declare, the Gentiles who faithfully ſerved God accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law written in their hearts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15, 16, 26. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> found as good an acceptation with God, as the Jewes that ſerved him according to the Letter of the Law delivered unto them; Nothing can be inferred from hence, to prove that God in the eſtate of nature loveth one man more than another, ſo as to neceſſitate his ſalvation rather than another</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> The Scriptures declare, <hi>Titus</hi> 3.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. That God calleth and ſaveth ſome men, not according to their workes: but according to his Grace which was given them before the world, but hee doth not ſo call and ſave all; therefore he doth reſpect the perſons of ſome men above others?</p>
               <p>For Anſwer to this Objection, I ſhall only endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour briefly to clear the Scripture alleadged for the countenance thereof, the firſt of which is <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wherein is declared, Firſt, what the Cretians were, before the Grace of God in Chriſt was made knowne unto them, (to wit) fooliſh, diſobedient, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119970:12"/>
divers luſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> verſ. 3. Secondly, what they became, after this Grace of God was revealed unto them, <hi>(viz.)</hi> they were regenerated and renewed by the holy Ghoſt. Thirdly, the benefit that did redound unto them thereby, <hi>(viz.)</hi> they were juſtified and made heires according to the hope of eternall life. The ſumme whereof, I take to be this. That the love and kindneſſe of God in Chriſt towards men, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto them in the Miniſtery of the Apoſtles, verſ. 4. They were thereby taught and perſwaded (not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily enforced by a power which they could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt) to deny all ungodlineſſe and worldy luſts (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in before they lived) and to live righteouſly, ſoberly, and godly, in this preſent evil World. And hereupon (foraſmuch as the ſame Apoſtle ſheweth that godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath the promiſe of the World to come) they obteined the hope and aſſurance of eternal life. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Titus</hi> 2.11, 12, 13. Which I take to be the natural expoſition of this text.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is ſaid that they were renewed by the Holy Ghoſt, it muſt not be conceived that they were irreſiſtably ſo renewed thereby: Becauſe it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident that the Spirit as it is vouchſafed for theſe ends doth not ſo operate in any men. According to the Scriptures the Spirit is communicated unto men, only theſe two wayes.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Miniſterially in the preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, to inſtruct men in the knowledge of the ſame; and from thence to leade them to the unfeigned obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereof. In which reſpect Jeſus Chriſt who ſpake not of himſelfe, but according as the Spirit of God that was upon him, wherewith hee was Anointed to preach the Goſpel, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. taught him, what hee
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119970:13"/>
ſhould ſay, and what hee ſhould ſpeake, <hi>John</hi> 12.49. ſaith, The words that I ſpeak unto you they are Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 6.63. So likewiſe the Miniſtery of the Apoſtles, wherein they delivered nothing but what they had heard or ſeen, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1. nor ſpake otherwiſe than according as the Spirit gave them utterance, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.4.) Is called the miniſtration of the Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8. and in like manner, in 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17, 18. the ſpirit is ſaid to preach repentance to the World in the dayes of <hi>Noah.</hi> And thus the naturall man is inſtructed in the things of the Spirit of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.13, 14.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Actually to thoſe that have received and ſubjected themſelves to the obedience of the Goſpel, (the Spirits inſtruction.) Repent and be Baptized, and ye ſhall receive the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. Have ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Holy Ghoſt ſince ye believed? <hi>Acts</hi> 19.2. In whom alſo after that ye believed, ye were ſealed with that holy Spirit of promiſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.12, 13. For ye are all the Sonnes of God by Faith in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.26. And becauſe ye are Sons, God hath ſent forth the Spirit of his Son into your hearts, <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.6.</p>
               <p>By the firſt of theſe wherein the Spirit by doctrine with ſignes and wonders for the confirmation thereof, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3, 4. Speaketh to the eares and eyes of men, graciouſly and lovingly ſtriving thereby, to convert them from their evill wayes; <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3. beſeeching them by all the mercies of God to preſent themſelves living ſacrifices unto him, holy and acceptable, which is their reaſonable ſervice, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. hee enforceth none in any ſuch ſort, but that poſſibly they may reſiſt and rebell againſt him therein: according as the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites are often charged. Ye ſtiff-necked and uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119970:13"/>
in hearts and eares (ſaith <hi>Steven</hi> ſpeaking un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them) ye doe alwaies reſiſt the holy Ghoſt, as your Fathers did, ſo doe yee <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51.</p>
               <p>They rebelled againſt, and vexed his holy Spirit, therefore he was turned to be their enemy, and fought againſt them, <hi>Eſay.</hi> 63.10. Yea, ſo far may the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of men heerin be extended, as not only wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and ſtubbornly to reſiſt and oppoſe; but moſt maliciouſly to blaſpheme him, and to attribute his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doctrines and wonders to <hi>Beelzebub</hi> the prince of Devils, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.24-27. <hi>John</hi> 8.48.</p>
               <p>Nor yet in the ſecond place, are any of thoſe who are actually poſſeſſed with the holy Ghoſt neceſſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereby to the obedience thereof; as is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly implyed, firſt, in thoſe many exhortations contained in the Scriptures. To walke in the Spirit. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.16. Not quench the Spirit. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.19. Nor grieve the holy Spirit, whereby ye are ſeal'd to the day of redemption. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly &amp; more eſpecially in thoſe Scriptures wherein it is clearly ſuppoſed (&amp; by the Apoſtles of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt taken for granted) that thoſe perſons who have been made pertakers of the Holy Ghoſt, may fall away from the obedience of it, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.4. doe deſpite unto it, <hi>heb.</hi> 1.29. and ſo defile their bodies the temples of it, as to bring the ſoreſt deſtruction &amp; condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon themſelves by reaſon thereof. Know ye not (ſaith the apoſtle) that ye are the temple of God, and that the ſpirit of <hi>God</hi> dwelleth in you? If any man defile the Temple of God, him ſhall God deſtroy. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16, 17. compare here with <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.29.</p>
               <p>And this more evidently may ſerve to demonſtrate that the Spirit in the Miniſtery thereof doth not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119970:14"/>
regeneration and purity in any; for if that it ſhould enforce purity in the uncleane, much more ſhould it preſerve purity in thoſe that are clean, and become temples thereunto.</p>
               <p>And therefore when it is ſaid, That the Cretians were renewed by the holy Ghoſt, it muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that they were renewed thereby no otherwiſe than through their diligent hearkning unto &amp; receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bleſſed doctrine thereof, revealed unto them by the Apoſtles preaching. From whence it is, that the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle the ſecond chap. verſe 22. writing unto Believers, thus expreſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; Having purified your own ſouls in obeying of the truth through the Spirit: Plainly intimating, that no man is renewed by the Spirit any otherwiſe than through their applying themſelves unto the doctrine and inſtruction thereof.</p>
               <p>The other Text is 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9. (the words whereof are theſe) Who hath ſaved us and called us with an holy calling, not according to our workes, but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own purpoſe and grace that was given us in Chriſt before the world. Which will not prove that God doth neceſſitate the faith and ſalvation of any man, ſeeing that that the grace, that was given to the perſons heer ſpoken of before the world, by which they were called and ſaved, in verſe the 10. is declared to be none other, than the grace that was manifeſted by Chriſt at his appearing, (ſo alſo in <hi>Titus</hi> 1.1, 2, 8.) and therefore by the latter we are to meaſure the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; &amp; by the grace manifeſted, judge &amp; determine what that grace was that was given them before the world.</p>
               <p>Now the grace of God towards man-kinde; mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by Chriſt at his appearance, is by <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119970:14"/>
2.11, 12. (before cited) thus diſcribed, The grace of <hi>God</hi> (ſaith he) that bringeth ſalvation to all men, hath appeared teaching us, that denying ungodlineſſe and worldly luſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to looke for the bleſſed hope and glorious appearing of the great God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; which generall deſcription in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scriptures is unfoulded into theſe particulars <hi>(viz.)</hi> That God ſo loved the world that he ſent his Son to be a Saviour thereof. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16, 17. And on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe by his death to deſtroy death, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. and therely deliver man from the curſe of the Law conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. of which all men ſtood guilty. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23. And by his reſurrection to bring life &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality to light. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. And in that eſtate to prepare manſions of glory and happineſſe, to be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of all thoſe that repent, believe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That is to ſay, That love God for his grace and mercie manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards them, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.19. Which conſiſteth in keeping his commandments. 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.3. Or in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Jeſus Chriſt being revealed unto them, and keeping his precepts. <hi>John</hi> 15.10. And that thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, believing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> men are required with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to hope, and with patience to waite for the promiſed Salvation, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19, 20, 21. &amp; 4.17. <hi>Titus</hi> 2.11, 12, 13. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.36.</p>
               <p>This then being the ſubſtance of the grace of God manifeſted by Chriſt at his appearing; the grace that was given to men before the world, is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood as followeth, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That God forth of his rich grace, pity, and compaſſion, conſidering all mankinde fallen from their firſt eſtate, and become guilty of everlaſting death; reſolved to ſend his Son into the World, to redeem them from thence, to reſtore them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119970:15"/>
again to immortality, to prepare for them therein a heavenly Kingdome, to open unto them a way there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into, to invite them to walke therein, and walking therein, in the end to give them the poſſeſſion thereof. According to which grace <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> were called and ſaved, and not according to their workes of righteouſneſſe by the Law; which is all that can ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally be inferred from this Scripture.</p>
               <p>And this is further confirmed by that which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the 13. verſe, where <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth <hi>Timothy,</hi> To hold faſt the forme of ſound words which he had heard of him in faith and love which is in Chriſt Jeſus, which exhortation ſeemeth to be grounded upon the turning away from the truth of many in <hi>Aſia,</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned verſe 15. the which would be altogether inper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent (as alſo that caution which he giveth him, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19. To hold faith and a good conſcience where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome had made ſhipwrack) If that before in the 9. verſe (as it is pretended) he had concluded that God in his eternall purpoſe had decreed to neceſſitate and enforce his faith and ſalvation, for where it is known there is no danger of miſcarriage, there is no ground to exhort to beware, or to admoniſh him to hold faſt, when both the admoniſher and the admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed underſtand that God hath decreed not to ſuffer him to let goe his hold if that he would.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> If that God doth not inforce men to believe, and ſo inforce their ſalvation thereby; then man is the author of his owne ſalvation.</p>
               <p>This conſequence is badly collected: As well might it be ſaid, that man is the author of his owne ſubſiſtance in this life, becauſe the food wherewith his life is mainteyned and preſerved is not brought unto
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119970:15"/>
his hand, minced and violently put into his mouth by the immediate hand of God.</p>
               <p>There are two things required to the Salvation of men <hi>(viz.)</hi> Gods Grace in Jeſus Chriſt, and mans obedience thereunto; as no man is ſaved by the former without the later, ſo neither can any man be ſaved by the later without the former. That no man can be ſaved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Grace of God in Chriſt, appeares in this: That no man is able to deliver himſelf from the curſe of the Law, raiſe himſelfe from corruption to immortality, create and ſet up that Glorious Fabrick of the World to come, or that Heavenly Jeruſalem which is to bee poſſeſſed therein, for theſe, as alſo for his owne being, the meanes of his Salvation, the promiſes of Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Juſtification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> through Faith and obedience every man muſt acknowledge himſelfe to be infinitely engaged to the unſpeakable mercy and goodneſſe of God in Chriſt. And that no man is ſaved by the Grace of God, without his obedience and conformity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, appeareth from hence. That men are puniſhed with damnation, for turning the Grace of God into wantonneſſe, <hi>Jude</hi> 4. For neglecting Salvation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. And walking in darkneſſe when light is come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, <hi>John</hi> 3.19. Upon which ground it is, that <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> thus exhorteth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16. Take heed unto thy ſelfe, and to thy doctrine, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue therein; for in ſo doing thou ſhalt both ſave thy ſelfe, and them that hear thee. And yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, foraſmuch as we our ſelves, the meanes which is improved, and the end thereof which is Salvation, is all of God; we are by the Scriptures inſtructed to attribute the honour and glory thereof wholly unto him. He giveth us (ſaith the Apoſtle,) 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17. (ſpeaking of the things of this life procured no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119970:16"/>
than through a laborious induſtry in the uſe of meanes) richly all things to enjoy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> That it cannot ſtand with the love of God unto all, to enforce ſome men to believe and not all.</head>
               <p>IF that God ſhould neceſſitate the Faith and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome men and not others, it would argue a repugnancy in the Doctrine of his love to man-kinde; unto whom he hath expreſſed an equall affection, in giving his Son a Saviour for all, and in deſiring the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of all.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That God ſent his Sonne into the World to ſave the World, appeareth by ſeverall plaine Texts of Scripture, as <hi>John</hi> 3.17. God ſent not his Son in to the World to condemne the World; but that the World through him might be ſaved, and <hi>John</hi> 6.11. I am, ſaith Chriſt, the living Bread which came down from Heaven; If any man eate of this Bread, he ſhall live for ever. And the bread that I ſhall give is my Fleſh, which I will give for the life of the World. Againe in <hi>John</hi> 12.47. If any man, ſaith he, heare my words and believe not, I judge him nor, for I came not into the world to judge the world, but to ſave the world. And in the 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5, 6. the Apoſtle ſaith, There is one God, and one Mediator between God
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119970:16"/>
and men, the Man Chriſt Jeſus; who gave himſelfe a Ranſome for all.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is by ſome objected, That by the World here ſpoken of, is not to be underſtood the whole lumpe of man-kinde, but only the Elect, a part thereof; and that by this terme (all) is not meant e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular man and woman in the world, but only ſome of all ſorts, &amp;c. The Scripture as it were foreſeeing this objection, addeth in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.9. That Chriſt taſted death for every man. And in the 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.1. That as there were falſe prophets among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: even ſo there ſhall be falſe teachers amongſt you, who privily ſhall bring in damnable hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them; and bring upon themſelves ſwift deſtruction. And <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.15. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy not with thy meat him for whom Chriſt dyed. And 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.11. Through thy knowledge ſhall the weake brother periſh for whom Chriſt dyed. Plainly intimating, that Chriſt dyed not only for the Elect (as they uſe to ſay) but for every man; for thoſe that deny him are deſtroyed, periſh, and are damned.</p>
               <p>And furthermore, whereas it is objected, That the perſons here ſpoken of, were not really of the number of thoſe for whom Chriſt dyed; only in the judgement of charity were ſo reputed.</p>
               <p>The Scriptures affordeth unto us divers evident grounds, to prove that Chriſt came into the World to ſave every particular perſon therein, without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As Firſt, the Goſpel is declared to be glad tydings unto all, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.10. And Secondly, is commanded therefore to be preached unto all, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Marke</hi> 16.15. And Thirdly, all men to whom it is preached, are required to believe it, <hi>Marke</hi> 16.16.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119970:17"/>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.20. And Fourthly, Such as doe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and give obedience unto it, are threatned with damnation, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.4. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8. And Fiftly, thoſe that have had it preached unto them, and refuſed to give obedience thereunto, are declared to judge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unworthy of everlaſting life, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46. and to neglect Salvation, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.3.</p>
               <p>Now foraſmuch as the Goſpel in generall is none other than the fruits of Chriſts death, &amp; that Salvation in particular is otherwiſe altogether impoſſible; it could not in the nature thereof be glad tydings unto all, nor in equity or juſtice be proclamed unto all; nor the obedience thereof be required of all; nor diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence thereunto be puniſhable in all; nor could it tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſaid, That thoſe that are damned for their diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience unto it, have neglected Salvation, if that Chriſt had not ſhed his Bloud for all.</p>
               <p>And furthermore, whereas it is replyed by ſome, That although Chriſt dyed for all, yet his death was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended only to ſave the Elect.</p>
               <p>It is by God declared, that he ſent his Son into the world forth of his love to man-kinde; to the end that thereby they might be ſaved, (for ſo ſaith the Scripture) God ſo loved the world, that he ſent his only begotten Son, <hi>&amp;c. John</hi> 3.16.</p>
               <p>And for the further confirmation of all mens Faith in this behalfe, he moſt ſolemnly profeſſeth, yea, and having no other to ſwear by, he ſweareth by Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, That he deſireth nor only the Salvation of thoſe that are ſaved; but of thoſe alſo who through con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of his goodneſſe, dye in their ſins and periſh, as we may reade in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. As I live ſaith the Lord God, I have no pleaſure in the death of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119970:17"/>
wicked, but that the wicked turne from his way and live: Turne ye, turne ye, from your evill wayes, for why will ye dye O Houſe of Iſrael? And herewithall accordeth the teſtimonies of his ſervants, in the 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3, 4. This is ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> good and acceptable in the ſight of God our Saviour (to wit) That we ſhould pray for all men, verſ. 1, 2. becauſe he would have all men to be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the Truth. And <hi>Peter</hi> in his Second Epiſtle the 3. chap. 9. to the ſame effect ſaith, The Lord is not ſlack concerning his promiſe (as ſome men count ſlackneſſe) but is long ſuffering to us wards, not willing that any ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, but that all ſhould come to repentance, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to Salvation, as the end thereof.</p>
               <p>Now as there is nothing more oppoſite than yea, and nay, (which as the Apoſtle informeth us in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19, 20. Is not in Jeſus Chriſt or in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God made in under the New Covenant:) ſo can there be nothing more repugnant to the Doctrine of Gods Love to mankinde expreſſed, in ſending his Son into the Word, that the world through him might be ſaved, and in his oath whereby he profeſſeth, that he would not have any thereof to periſh, &amp;c. Then this Doctrine which ſaith, That God doth neceſſarily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force ſome men to believe, to the end they may bee ſaved: and denieth ſufficient meanes unto others to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able them to believe, to the end they may be damned. The Firſt ſaith, That he loveth and deſireth the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all alike, and would have none to periſh. The latter ſaith, That he deſireth but the Salvation of a few in ſpeciall, and willeth the damnation of many. The firſt ſaith, That through the mercy of God vouchſafed in Jeſus Chriſt, every man may poſſibly be ſaved. The
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119970:18"/>
later ſaith, That no man can poſſibly obtaine Salvation thereby, without a ſpeciall aſſiſtance vouchſafed unto him, to enable him to believe, &amp;c. and ſo deny Jeſus Chriſt to be the Doore and way to eternall life, and concludeth man-kinde (whom he came into the world to ſave) as incapable of obtaining the end of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, as if he had not at all come into the world to be their Saviour: And ſo in a word maketh the Death of Jeſus Chriſt in relation to the Salvation of man-kinde of none effect: And the ſolemne Oath of Almighty God, as touching his deſire of the Salvation of all, and the death of none (with reverence be it ſpoken) worſe then jeſuiticall deluſion and equivocation; which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone may ſerve as a ſufficient evidence againſt this Opinion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> How the Doctrine of Gods enforcing men to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, leadeth the Reprobates to Blaſphemy againſt God, and maketh them excuſable in their condemnation.</head>
               <p>IF God ſhould neceſſitate the Salvation of ſome men, and not others, it would fill the Reprobates with Blaſphemy againſt him, by reaſon of their condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion contrary to the Scriptures. From this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That in the point of Salvation he doth that for others, which he refuſed to doe for them, and yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119970:18"/>
that he hath done as much for them in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe as he could.</p>
               <p>That God profeſſeth, that he hath done as much for the Reprobates to make them fruitfull to Salvation, as he could: The words of the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> in his 5. chap. doe plainly declare, I will ſing to my wel-beloved (ſaith he) a Song of my beloved touching his Vineyard: My wel-beloved hath a Vineyard in a very fruitfull hill, and he fenced it, and gathered out the ſtones thereof, and planted it with the choiſeſt Vine, and built a Tower in the midſt of it, and alſo made a Wine-preſſe therein; and he looked that it ſhould bring forth Grapes, and it brought forth wilde Grapes. And now, O Inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and men of <hi>Judah,</hi> judge I pray you betwixt me and my Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, what could have been done more to my Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, that I have not done to it? Wherefore when I looked, that it ſhould have brought forth Grapes, it brought forth wilde Grapes: And now go to, I will tell you what I will doe to my Vineyard, &amp;c. Under which ſimilitude, the Prophet declareth unto the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> whoſe deſtruction for their unfruitfulneſſe &amp; diſobedience towards God, he denounceth in the following part of the chapter, from the 8. v. &amp;c. That God to make them fruitfull un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all good workes, to prevent their deſtruction, and to bring them to eternall life, had vouchſafed and granted unto them all convenient and neceſſary means conducing to thoſe ends. Inſomuch that when hee appealeth unto them for judgement therein, before he proceedeth to pronounce his definitive ſentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, they are left altogether ſpeechleſſe, not having any thing to reply unto God in their owne
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119970:19"/>
behalfe; whereas if their underſtandings had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed that any neceſſary meanes had been wanting unto them, without which they could not poſſibly ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto God that which he requireth of them; or that he had not vouchſafed unto them as effectuall meanes, as he did unto others in the like caſe; their anſwer might have been ready in words to this effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Lord we are poore helpleſſe Creatures (who alone by reaſon of thy decree, in reference to <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion, which we could no wayes poſſibly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent) are made altogether uncapable by any ſuch meanes as thou affordeſt unto us, to doe any thing pleaſing or acceptable in thy ſight, no not ſo much as to thinke one good thought; and this Lord thou knoweſt, and from the conſideration thereof, thou giveſt unto ſuch and ſuch men and women, thy good Spirit; whereby they are enabled to the doing of thoſe things that thou requireſt of us; without which Spirit, our inflicted condemnation is altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoydable. And therefore if that we muſt periſh, it's only for thy wills ſake, and neither for omitting or miſdoing any thing that we were able rightly to doe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas, therefore the Scriptures informeth us, that when the greateſt enemies of Almighty God, ſhal take into their moſt ſtrict and ſevereſt examination, all his ſayings and proceedings againſt them; that forth of their owne mouthes, like unto thoſe wicked Husband-men (in the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.40, 41.) they ſhall fully acquit and juſtifie him in them all. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.4. And that we are thereby alſo plainely informed, That if our conſciences doe not accuſe and condemne us, we have peace with God, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.21. And ſo
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119970:19"/>
conſequently that then he will not condemne us; we are hereby neceſſarily led to this concluſion, That Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is not confered upon men through neceſſity: nor that it is any otherwiſe to be obteined, than through mens improvement of the meanes granted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Gods not doing ſo much for the Reprobates as he doth for others, is no direct cauſe of Blaſphemy in them, in regard that he is not thereunto bound; ſo that if they Blaſpheme, it's without cauſe on Gods part.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, Wherein any mans conſcience accuſeth him not as touching ſuch things whereof he is accuſed and condemned by another, he is inevitably compelled to contradict and gain-ſay in that reſpect: And ſo likewiſe, if that the Reprobates ſhould be condemned by God for impenitency and the workes thereof, and yet in their owne conſciences be infallibly aſſured that repentance was altogether impoſſible unto them, they ſhould therein directly (nil they will they) be inforced to contradict and gain-ſay in ſuch their condemnation; which in the Scripture ſenſe is none otherwiſe than Blaſphemy, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.45.</p>
               <p>Secondly, And therefore although that God as hee is Lord and Creator of all, cannot be bound unto any of his creatures, yet conſidering that he doth not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to condemne any of them; thereby to exerciſe (like a cruell tyrant) his power and prerogative upon them, but only to puniſh them for their voluntary and wilfull diſobedience againſt him; for the Honour of his Iuſtice he is abſolutely bound not to condemne them for any ſuch thing which is impoſſible unto them, becauſe that then his Iuſtice cannot appear nor
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119970:20"/>
bee acknowledged by them in their condemnation, as he hath declared it ſhall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> How the Doctrine of Gods enforcing men to believe tendreth the exhortations of God to the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, and his lamentations for their damnation hatefull and odious.</head>
               <p>IF that Faith and Salvation were attainable only through an neceſſitating power, and not through mens improvement of the meanes, it would render all the invitations and exhortations of God to the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates to heare his voyce and partake of Salvation by Chriſt contemptable and all his lamentations for their refuſall thereof; and their deſtruction thereupon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, hatefull and odious, becauſe that ſuch exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, invitations and lamentations (if real) are alwaies moſt infallible arguments of the ſtrongeſt affection, towards thoſe perſons in whoſe behalfe they are made, but are not ſuch towards them if that Repentance, Faith, &amp;c. be attainable only through neceſſity, and not through their improvement of the meanes afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto them, they otherwiſe being wholly uncapable of themſelves, of obeying his exhortations, &amp;c. And God unwilling to grant them that aſſiſtance which hee knew to be neceſſary for the avoyding of their threatned deſtruction, notwithſtanding ſuch his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:119970:20"/>That God exhorteth and inviteth the Reprobates, to hear his voice, and partake of the ſalvation prepared in Chriſt, the Scriptures doe plentifully declare unto us, as in <hi>Proverbs</hi> 1.20, to the 24. Wiſdome cryeth without, ſhe uttereth her voyce in the ſtreets, ſhe cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the chief place of the concourſe, in the opening of the Gates in the City ſhe uttereth her words, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, How long ye ſimple ones, will ye love ſimplicity, and ſcorners delight in their ſcorning, and fooles hate knowledge? Turne ye at my reproof, behold I will pour out my Spirit (or minde) unto you (as ſome reade) I will make known my words unto you. And <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Wiſdome hath builded her a Houſe, ſhe hath hewen her out ſeven Pillars, ſhe hath killed her Beaſts, ſhe hath mingled her Wine, ſhe hath alſo furniſhed her Table, ſhe hath alſo ſent forth her mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, ſhe cryeth upon the higheſt places of the City, who ſo is ſimple let him turne in hither; as for him that wanteth underſtanding, ſhe ſaith to him, come eat of my bread and drinke of the Wine which I have ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, forſake the fooliſh, and live, and go in the way of underſtanding. And <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Kingdom of Heaven is like unto a certaine King, which made a Marriage for his Son, and ſent forth his Servants to cal thoſe that were bidden to the Wedding, and they made light of it, and he ſent forth other Servants, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Tell them which are bidden, behold I have prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red my dinner, my Oxen and my fatlings are killed, and all things are ready, come unto the Marriage, but they made light of it.</p>
               <p>And that the Lord doth expreſſe himſelfe in way of ſorrow and lamentation, for the diſobedience of men to his loving invitations, exhortations, and their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119970:21"/>
puniſhment following thereupon, is as manifeſt as the former. In <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.5, 6. he thus ſpeaketh; Who ſhall viſite thee, Oh Ieruſalem? Or who ſhall bemone thee? Or who ſhall go aſide to aſke how thou doeſt? Thou haſt forſakes me, ſaith the Lord, thou haſt gone backward, therefore will I ſtretch out my hand againſt thee, and deſtroy thee; I am weary with repenting. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 81.8-11-13. Hear O my people and I will teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy unto thee; O Iſrael, if thou wilt hearken unto me: But my people would not hearken unto my voice, and Iſrael would have none of me: O that my people had hearkned unto me, and Iſrael had walked in my waies. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. Turne ye turne ye, why will yee dye O houſe of Iſrael? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.32. I have no pleaſure in the death of him that dyeth, ſaith the Lord God, wherefore turne your ſelves and live. <hi>Luke</hi> 19.41. And when he was come neer he beheld the City and wept over it, ſaying, If thou haddeſt known, even thou, at leaſt in this thy day, the things that belong unto thy peace. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37. O Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, that kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt the Prophets and ſtoneſt them that are ſent unto thee, how often would I have gathered thy children together even as a Hen gathereth her chicken, and ye would not? <hi>Hoſeah</hi> 6.5. O <hi>Epraim,</hi> what ſhall I doe unto thee? O <hi>Judeah</hi> what ſhall I do unto thee? For your goodneſſe is as the morning cloud, and as the early dew it goeth away. 2 <hi>chron.</hi> 26.14, 15, 16. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over all the chief of the Prieſts and the people, tranſgreſſed very much after the abominations of the Heathen; and the Lord God of their Fathers ſent unto them by his Meſſengers, riſing up betimes, and ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe he had compaſſion on his People, and on his dwelling place; but they mocked the Meſſengers
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119970:21"/>
of God, and deſpiſed his word, and miſuſed his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, untill the wrath of the Lord aroſe againſt them till there was no remedy.</p>
               <p>Now as nothing can poſſibly be ſaid by God to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him more gracious, loving, kinde and pitifull to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards miſerable men, or more to endear and enflame their affections towards him, than what is here by him expreſſed, being underſtood according to theſe rules which he hath given unto us to judge of his love and goodneſſe by; in regard that ſuch expreſſions doe abundantly demonſtrate that he unfainedly and from his very heart (as it were) deſireth that wee all ſhould hear his voice, obey his counſell, partake of the benefits of his Son, obtain ſalvation through him, and that there is no defect, nor any thing wanting on his part that can be judged or any waies conceived neceſſary or requiſite to enable us thereunto, and conſequently to avoide and eſcape the wrath that is to come: ſo neither on the contrary is it poſſible, that the Almighty God ſhould preſent himſelfe to his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turs more hateful &amp; odious then by any blaſphemy that his moſt inveterate and malicious enemies forth of their deepeſt deſpight and hatred againſt him, can any any waies imagine or foment, which would be by ſuch his exhortations and lamentations, where the obedience and duty that he requireth of men to their ſalvation, and the eſcaping of perdition in the world to come are impoſſible unto them: forasmuch as then all his love and affection, pity and compaſſion therein manifeſted, could be eſteemed no other then meere mockage, hipocriſie, deluſion and cruelty in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree, becauſe that whileſt he pretendeth, the greateſt love, he ſhould beare the greateſt hatred;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119970:22"/>
whileſt he pretendeth to ſeeke their ſalvation, he ſhould ſecretly aime at and intend their damnation; whileſt he pretendeth to lament their miſery, he ſhould laugh thereat, rejoyce and delight therein, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from eternity without any reſpect to their miſdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings utterly excluded them out of his favour, ſhut and faſt ſealed them up under his wrath, hatred and ſoreſt indignation; and from thence denying unto them the neceſſary meanes of their ſalvation, which being the true and naturall conſequence of that doctrine, which aſſerteth ſalvation to be through neceſſity, and not through mens voluntary improvement of the means; may admoniſh all men that tender the glory and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, to beware thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> The exhortations and invitations of God to Reprobates to partake of good things prepared in Chriſt are not contemptible and odious, conſidering that good things are prepared in Chriſt, unto which the Reprobates are invited, which retain their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, though they be rejected.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Its not the goodnes of the thing prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Chriſt, that can free the exhortations of God to Reprobates, to partake thereof from contempt: if that God forth of his hatred againſt them, ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to exclude them from the participation of them; becauſe that thereby the Reprobates ſhould be abuſed with a ſpecious ſhew of love towards them, when as nothing but hatred is intended to them; which muſt needs render ſuch exhortations odious unto them. <hi>Abſaloms</hi> good cheare rendreth his invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to <hi>Ammon</hi> to eate thereof far worſe than open hatred. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.26-28.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Therefore I further anſwer, That it is impoſſible
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119970:22"/>
that God who abhorreth nothing more than mens drawing neare unto him with their mouthes, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring him with their lips, when their hearts are far from him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.20. <hi>Iſay</hi> 1.13, 14. <hi>Amos</hi> 5.23. And who hath inſtructed all men not to eate the bread or deſire the dainty meates of him that hath an evill eye, but to contemne his invitations (eate eate) when his heart is not with them. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.6, 7. That he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould ſo practiſe, doe the thing which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſteth, and exhort men to eate in the ſame caſe, wherein he willeth them to abſtain; he cannot lye, becauſe he is truth it ſelfe, <hi>Titus</hi> 1.1. therefore as he ſpeaketh ſo he thinketh, and like as he pretendeth ſo he meaneth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ob.</hi> 2. Secondly, concerning the lamentations of God in reſpect of thoſe that periſh, it is objected, That they ſerve onely to expreſſe the remedileſnes of their miſery: And that he is not delighted with their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment as they are his creatures, but with the glory of his juſtice which ſhineth in their wickedneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The firſt part of which objection <hi>(viz.)</hi> That the lamentations of God in the behalfe of thoſe that periſh, ſerve only to expreſſe the remedileſneſs of their miſery, rightly underſtood may be admitted; But I deſire to know, whither their miſery be remedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in reſpect of themſelves, or in reſpect of God? whether for want of meanes ſufficient vouchſafed by God to prevent their miſery, or through their wilfull neglect and abuſe thereof? In the latter ſenſe I grant the objection to be good; For he that neglecteth the grace of God in Chriſt vouchſafed unto him in this life, by what meanes ſhall his miſery be prevented in that which is to come, damnation in hell being the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119970:23"/>
penalty thereof? From which there is neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption nor Redeemer made known unto us. But that their miſery ſhould be remedileſſe for want of mercy ſufficient vouchſafed unto them in this life for the prevention thereof, may not be magnified, becauſe it's inconſiſtant with the integrity of Gods pure nature (diſcovered unto us in his Atributes of Truth, Love, Goodneſſe, Mercy and Iuſtice) to make lamentations in the behalfe of his periſhing creatures, when as the reaſon thereof lyeth ſimply and wholy in himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Whereas it is further ſuggeſted, That theſe lamentations are intended to expreſſe, That God is not delighted with the puniſhment of his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but with the glory of his juſtice, which ſhineth in their palpable wickedneſs; its moſt abſurd, Becauſe that if God ſhould be delighted to have men wicked as they are his creatures, he muſt needs much more be delighted with their puniſhment, as they are his creatures, the puniſhment of wickedneſs being the moſt proper exerciſe of his juſtice: And therefore if the glory of his juſtice againſt the honour of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, ſhould engage him to deny his grace unto his creatures, to the intent that they might be wicked, it muſt needs much more engage him to puniſh them being wicked.</p>
               <p>Beſides, the Scriptures doe plainly informe us, That God doth not onely lament the puniſhment of his creatures, but their ingratitude and wickedneſſe alſo as the cauſe thereof. In <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To the ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Iſraelites he thus ſpeaketh.</p>
               <p>I remember thee, the day of thy eſpouſals, when thou wenteſt after me in the wilderneſſe in a Land that was not ſowne, verſ. 5. What iniquities have your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119970:23"/>
found in me, that they are gone far from me, and are walked after vanities and are become vaine? verſ. 6. Neither ſaid they where is the Lord that brought us up out of the Land of <hi>Egypt?</hi> That led us through the Wilderneſſe through a Land of Deſarts and of Pits, through a Land of drought, and of the ſhaddow of death, through a Land that no man paſſed through, and where no man dwelt, verſ. 7. And I brought you into a plentifull Country, to eate the fruit thereof, and the goodneſſe thereof, but where ye entred ye defiled my Land, and made mine Heritage an abomination. The Prieſt ſaith not, where is the Lord, and they that hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Law knew me not; the Paſtors alſo tranſgreſſed againſt me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> verſ. 12, 13. Be aſtoniſhed O Heavens at this, and be horribly afraid, be ye very deſolate ſaith the Lord. For my people have committed two e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, they have forſaken me, the fountaine of living wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and hewen to themſelves broken Ciſterns that can hold no water. verſ. 31. O Generation, ſee the Word of the Lord: have I been a Wilderneſſe unto Iſrael? A Land of darkneſſe? Wherefore ſay my people, We are Lords, we wil come no more unto thee? Can a Maide forget her Ornaments, or a Bride her Attire? Yet my people have forgotten me dayes without number. <hi>Iſay.</hi> 1.2. Hear O Heavens, and give ear O Earth, for the Lord hath ſpoken; I have nouriſhed and brought up Children, and they have rebelled againſt me. The Oxe knoweth his owner, and the Aſſe his Maſters cribbe: but Iſrael doth not know, my people doth not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Ah! ſinfull Nation, a people laden with iniquty, a ſeed of evill doers, Children that are corrupted, they have forſaken the Lord, they have provoked the holy one of Iſrael unto Anger. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 13.27. Woe unto
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119970:24"/>
thee O Jeruſalem, wilt thou not be made clean? When ſhall it once be? How much more of this nature might be added? Such as reade the Scriptures know. Now that the goodneſſe of God ſhould thus cauſe him to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the wickedneſſe of men, and endeavour their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; and yet the glory of his Juſtice in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereunto, ſhould cauſe him to delight in their wickedneſſe; and from thence to deny them the means of repentance, cannot be ſuppoſed, becauſe that this would quite invert the teſtimony of S. <hi>James,</hi> chap. 2.13. And make judgement in God to glory and rejoyce againſt mercy: nor yet can it ſtand any better with the purity of God, to lament the wickedneſſe of thoſe whom he delighteth to have wicked, then for him to lament the damnation of thoſe, whom from eternity he hath excluded from his favour, and appointed thereunto. But ſecondly, I anſwer, That it is inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the nature of Gods juſtice, to delight in the wickedneſſe of any man, becauſe that juſtice it ſelfe can neither occaſion nor take delight in any thing that is unjuſt, or contrary to it ſelfe; as all ſuch things muſt needs be which are reprehended and puniſhed thereby, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1, 3, 21, 22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.3, 6. Therefore ſeeing that the juſtice of God is declared to be angry with, and provoked to wrath by the wickedneſſe, hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, and impenitency of men, <hi>Marke</hi> 3.5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.4, 5, 6, 7. It cannot poſſibly be pleaſed or delighted therein, or be any waies acceſſary thereunto, Either by working wickedneſſe in mens mindes, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.13. (As ſome men too raſhly affirme from theſe and ſuch like Scriptures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.18. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.28. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.40.) or by prohibiting meanes ſufficient for the prevention thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119970:24"/>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> God could have prevented both Angels and men from falling, and could recover all and every one of men, as well as any; which argueth that he would have ſome to periſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> What God as he is Almighty and Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent might have done, we will not diſpute, nor is it neceſſary to the preſent point: It is ſufficient to our purpoſe to prove, that God vouchſafed both to Men and Angels, means ſufficient to prevent their fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; the which, I ſuppoſe no rationall man will deny; ſeeing that whatſoever God hath impoſed upon his Creatures, by the Law of nature and neceſſity (as hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, drought, wearineſſe, eating, drinking, ſleeping, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) are neither offenſive, nor diſpleaſing to him; it being impoſſible, that he ſhould blame or finde fault with what himſelfe doth, or neceſſitateth his Creatures for to doe: ſo that if the fall of Men or Angels had been unavoidable by them, by the Law of their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, their falling had not been ſinfull in them, nor ſhould they ever have incurred the diſpleaſure of God in any reſpect, by reaſon thereof, no more than we now do by our eating, drinking, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>God Created both Angels and men in a mutable eſtate, ſufficiently able to doe whatſoever he required of them; and furniſhed them abundantly with argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his love and goodneſſe, to endear and engage them to the perpetuall love and obedience of himſelf; and yet withall ſubject, (or incident) through the want of conſideration of his goodneſſe towards them, to fall into ingratitude and diſobedience againſt him, becauſe that otherwiſe, neither the one nor the other could have been capable of manifeſting their fidelity and thankfulneſſe unto him their Lord and Creator, (as it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119970:25"/>
was moſt neceſſary they ſhould) for how ſhould he expreſſe his ſubjection and obedience, who cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly diſobey? And how God could have made a creature in ſuch an eſtate, wherein his love and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards him, and ſoveraignty over him, could not thankfully be acknowledged by him, cannot reaſonably be imagined. In which reſpect, it may juſtly be queſtioned, Whether God could have done any more to prevent the fall of angels and men, then what he did?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whereas it is implied, That God hath not recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Jeſus Chriſt, all and every of men (as well as any) from under the curſe of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion, it is not to be admitted, becauſe the Scriptures do informe us, That as in <hi>Adam</hi> all die, ſo in Chriſt, all are made alive, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. And that as by one mans offence, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment came upon all men to condemnation, even ſo by the righteouſnes of one, the free gift came upon al men, to the juſtification of life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.18. And that as the firſt man <hi>Adam</hi> was made a living ſoul, ſo the ſecond man <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> is made a quickning ſpirit, 1 <hi>Co.</hi> 15.45. But I ſuppoſe that by theſe words (God could recover all, and every man, as well as any) is to be underſtood only, That God could (if he were pleaſed) enforce the ſalvation of all, and every man, as well as ſome: wherin that is taken for granted, which is denied (to wit) that God doth neceſſitate the ſalvation of ſome particular men, and not others (which hath already, and ſhall hereafter be further diſproved:) And although that it cannot be denied, but that ſome men doe periſh, yet is it not therefore to be conceived, that they ſo periſh for want of means ſufficient to accompliſh their ſalvation, but by reaſon of their contempt thereof. All the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119970:25"/>
waies of God being mercy and truth, the goodneſſe of God is alwaies firſt exerciſed in providing means ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for the Salvation of men; but when his goodneſſe therein is deſpiſed, and his Grace turned into wantonneſſe; then, and not till then, doth his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and juſtice call for judgement and vengeance againſt the deſpiſers and contemners of him, as the Scriptures doe witneſſe, <hi>Jud.</hi> 3, 4, 5, 6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4, 5. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 26.14, 15, 16. In which reſpect it is that God is ſaid to be ſlow to anger, <hi>Nahum.</hi> 1.3. That he doth not willingly afflict nor grieve the Children of Men, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.33. That mercy glorieth againſt judgement, <hi>Iames.</hi> 2.13. And that his tender mercies are over all his workes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.9.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> How the opinion of enforcing Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance in men, oppoſeth the Wiſdome of God.</head>
               <p>IF that Repentance, Faith, &amp;c. were through neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and not attainable; only by the improvement of the means afforded, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the workes and Word of God; it would not ſtand with the Wiſdome of God, to expect and wait for the Repentance of men, as the Scriptures declare he doth: Becauſe that herein hee ſhould not looke for Figs of a Fig-Tree, according to the practice of Chriſt; But for Figs of Thornes, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119970:26"/>
Grapes of Thiſtles, which is much below the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of men; and therefore much more of God.</p>
               <p>That God doth expect and wait for Repentance from men, is plainly taught in the Scriptures, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.1, 2, My beloved (ſaith the Prophet, ſpeaking of God) hath a Vineyard in a very fruitfull hil; and he fenced it; and gathered out the ſtones thereof; and planted it with the choiceſt Vine, and built a Tower in the midſt of it; and alſo made a Wine-preſſe therein, and he looked that it ſhould bring forth Grapes, and it brought forth wilde Grapes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 13.6. And Jeſus ſpake alſo this parable: A certaine man had a Fig-Tree planted in his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, and he came and ſought fruit thereon, and found none; Then ſaid he to the dreſſer of the Vineyard, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold theſe three years I come ſeeking fruit on this Fig-Tree, and finde none; cut it down, why cumbreth. it the ground. <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.27. O Jeruſalem, wilt thou not be made cleane, when ſhall it once be?</p>
               <p>Now foraſmuch as wiſdome doth prohibite a man to expect the effect without the cauſe, or more from any cauſe, then can be effected thereby, or to wait for a plentiful harveſt in Summer, without plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſowing in the Winter; who can conceive that Almighty God the fountaine of all wiſdome, yea, who is wiſdome it ſelf, ſhould expect and wait for repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance from men, without vouchſafing unto them means ſufficient to anſwer his expectation therein! No man ſeeketh Figs of Thorns, or Grapes of Thiſtles, and ſhall God that maketh men wiſe, be conceived to be ſo far inferiour unto him in wiſdome, as to ſeek and expect repentance of man, it being no leſſe impoſſible to be found? Surely nothing can be leſſe imaginable;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119970:26"/>
And yet for the further prevention of ſuch diſhonour able thoughts concerning the God of all Wiſdome, the Scriptures before cited, note unto us theſe two things: Firſt, the ground upon which God doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect repentance from men, demonſtrated to us under the ſimilitude of a man planting his Vineyard in a fruitfull Hill, planting it with the choiceſt Vine, fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it, gathering out the ſtones, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As alſo under the ſimilitude of a Husband-man, dreſſing and digging about his Fig-Tree. Secondly, the time in which God expecteth repentance from men, which by Chriſt; in <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.34. (in which Parable he alludeth to <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5.1) is declared to be not untill the time of Vintage, and the more plainly to declare, how farre he is from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting from men that which is unreaſonable: in <hi>Luke</hi> 13.7. he uſeth theſe words, Theſe three years have I come ſeeking fruit and finde none, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Under which formes of ſpeech, the Lord doth inſtruct us, That as a wiſe Husband-man doth not expect to receive fruit from his Vineyard, without the uſe of all neceſſary means required thereunto, nor untill the ſeaſon of the year wherein his expectation may be anſwered; ſo neither doth he himſelf look for any thing more from men, then what he affordeth unto them ſufficient means and opportunity to effect.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing then that if repentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were no otherwiſe attainable then through the irreſiſtable ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Spirit: that all impenitent wicked and ungodly perſons from whom he expecteth repentance, ſhould neither have means nor any opportunity afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto them for that purpoſe, (for if that the means thereof doe neceſſarily accompliſh the ſame; then all thoſe that have that means muſt needs be enforced to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119970:27"/>
repentance thereby.) Therefore repentance muſt be acknowledged to be obtained only thorow the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of ſuch means which God vouchſafeth unto all, and the nature thereof be acknowledged to be ſuch, that poſſibly may be neglected by thoſe to whom it is granted, and from whence (repentance) the end thereof is expected, <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.21. I gave her ſpace (ſaith the ſpirit) to repent, and ſhe repented not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> How the commands of God in Scripture are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the opinion of Gods enforcing Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis doctrine (to wit of Gods neceſſitating re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) oppoſe the Commandments of God given unto men, whereby he requireth them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, believe in the name of his Sonne, work out their own ſalvation with fear and trembling. Now for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as God cannot oppoſe himſelf, therefore that which he requireth of men to doe, muſt needs be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and peculiar to them to perform.</p>
               <p>That God requireth every man to repent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident by the Scriptures, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.30. The times of this ignorance God winked at, but now he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all men every where to repent, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.23. And this is his Commandment, that we ſhould beleeve in the name of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. Work out your own ſalvation with fear and trembling whereby repentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is by God made the pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar work and duty of man, through the improvement of the means vouchſafed unto him for thoſe ends, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119970:27"/>
whereunto is the doctrine, which averreth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be the peculiar work of God, and not of men, That it is by God made the peculiar work of man, through the improvement of the means, appeareth from hence, that God threatneth condemnation to thoſe perſons, who thorow the uſe of ſuch means, as he afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth unto them for that end, do or did not repent, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.20, 21, 22. Then began he (ſaith the text, meaning Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus) to upbraid the Cities, wherein moſt of his mighty works were done, becauſe they repented not: Wo unto thee <hi>Corazin,</hi> Wo unto thee <hi>Bethſaida:</hi> for if the mighty works, which were done in you, had been done in <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sydon,</hi> they would have repented long agoe in ſack-cloth and aſhes. But I ſay unto you, it ſhall be more tolerable for <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sydon,</hi> in the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then for you. For it cannot be ſuppoſed, that God ſhould condemn men for not doing the thing which doth not peculiarly appertain unto them to doe: And that it is by the opinion of Gods neceſſitating re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> made the peculiar work of God is as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, the opinion it ſelf plainly intimating, Then no man by all his beſt endeavours in the uſe of the means, can poſſibly attain thereunto: which oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot be applied unto God, as proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from him, becauſe that in the Scriptures it is to be obſerved, that he is ſo far from requiring of men the doing of ſuch things, which peculiarly belong unto himſelf to perform, that in all ſuch caſes he requireth them to ſtand ſtill, and wait upon him for his help and ſalvation. As we may reade, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13. where by his Almighty power he made it his work to give the people paſſage thorow the red ſea, he commanded them that they ſhould not fear, but ſtand ſtill, and ſee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119970:28"/>
his ſalvation. As alſo in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.23. where having before undertaken to diſcomfit the hoaſt of the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims</hi> in the behalf of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> he commandeth <hi>David</hi> that he ſhould not move untill he heard the ſound of a going in the tops of the Mulbery trees: as alſo again, when he was pleaſed to make it his peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar work to deliver the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> forth of their captivity, he commanded them only to wait upon him with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence for their delivery from thence, <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.3.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Becauſe it is alſo to be obſerved, That when he uſeth the concurrence of man for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing of any worke, he alwaies diſtinguiſheth the work of man from that which belongeth to himſelf to perform therein: and whatſoever he requireth of them in ſuch caſes, that he will have to be performed by them: and will not himſelf do it for them.</p>
               <p>As firſt, when he gave the people in the wildernes water out of the rock, <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.8. he preciſely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> the work that he required of him thereunto. Take the rod (ſaith he) and gather the Aſſembly together, thou and <hi>Aaron</hi> thy brother, and ſpeak ye unto the rock before their eies, and it ſhall give forth his water.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Likewiſe when he promiſed to deliver the City of <hi>Jericho</hi> unto his people, for the over-throw of the walls thereof, he plainly and evidenty declared, what he required of them to that end, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5. Ye ſhall compaſſe the City (ſaith he) all ye men of warre, and goe about the City once; thus ſhalt thou doe ſix daies. And ſeven Prieſts ſhall bear before the Ark ſeven Trumpets of Rams-horns, and the ſeventh day ye ſhall compaſſe the City ſeven times, and the Prieſts ſhall blow with the Trumpets. And it ſhall
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119970:28"/>
come to paſſe, that when they make a long blaſt with the Rams-horns, and when ye hear the ſound of the Trumpets, all the people ſhall ſhout with a great ſhout, and the wall of the City ſhall fall.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, And alſo when he made it his work to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> and the other Nations, for their great and abominable wickedneſſe, and to give the poſſeſſion of their Land to the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he clearly manifeſted unto them, what he would have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed on their part for the accompliſhment thereof; They were to obſerve his Word, and to obey his voice: As we reade, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.20, 21, 22. and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular to goe armed before the Lord unto battel, <hi>Num.</hi> 32.20. And he himſelf would cauſe the hearts of their enemies to fail them for fear, and make them turn their backs upon them, untill they were deſtroyed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.27.</p>
               <p>And this he doth, Becauſe that he will not give his glory unto another, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.8. which would neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow upon his requiring of men, and aſſigning un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them the performance of thoſe things, which im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately concerneth himſelf, or by his not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing the work of man from his own, in ſuch acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, wherein his concurrence is required. In regard that no man can poſſibly aſcribe unto him the honour of that work, which is not evidently diſcovered to be wrought by him.</p>
               <p>Whereas therefore we finde that men are abſolutely commanded to repent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and are no where required to ſtand ſtill, or wait upon God, untill ſuch time as he ſhall neceſſitate them thereunto, nor yet can finde any diſtinction made therein, as that man ſhould doe this or that, and that God will doe the reſt: repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119970:29"/>
as it is conſidered, whether in the diſpoſition of the minde, or in the actions, and exerciſe thereof; muſt be concluded the peculiar work of men, by the uſe and improvement of the means vouchſafed unto them by God for that purpoſe; the which will further appear from theſe grounds.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe that the penitent ſhall riſe up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the impenitent, and condemn them; as appeareth by the words of Chriſt, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.41. The men of <hi>Nineveh</hi> (ſaith he) ſhall riſe up in judgement againſt this generation, and condemn them, becauſe they repented at the preaching of <hi>Jonas,</hi> and behold a greater then <hi>Jonas</hi> is here; which could not be, if that repentance were the peculiar work of God, and not of men, by the improvement of the means. For where there is no difference in men, but that which is enforced in them by God, the one can be no accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the other, in reſpect of any ſuch differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: for as he that did repent would not have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented, if he had not been enforced: ſo he that did not repent, would have repented, if that he had been enforced. And therefore the men of <hi>Nineveh,</hi> if they were enforced to repent, can be no greater an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation againſt the Iews for their impenitency in the day of judgement, then <hi>Benjamins</hi> brethren can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, in reſpect of the cup that was put into his ſack, againſt his will or procurement.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe the Scriptures doe plainly declare, That God doth not require of men, beyond what he giveth unto them, means to attain unto, as we may perceive in the Parable of the talents, in <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.15. where none are called to give an account before Chriſt at his coming, but thoſe to whom before hand he had deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119970:29"/>
his money to be improved, nor nothing requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of any of them, but proportionably to that which was delivered to them, to whom he giveth much, he asketh the more again, according to his ſaying, in <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.48. And ſo on the contrary, From whence it doth follow, That ſeeing repentance is required of all men, and that all men ſhall be accountable to God concerning the ſame, That therefore all men have the means of repentance vouchſafed unto them, &amp; that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance by the improvement therof peculiarly apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth unto them, and is no otherwiſe to be obtained.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Becauſe that the impenitent are charged with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt God in reſpect of their impenitency, which plainly argueth, repentance not only to be the peculiar work of man, but alſo within his power to be performed, rebellion being none other then a wilfull and ſtubborn refuſall of that known duty which a man is enabled to perform. And ſo much the words of the text do evidently declare, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 12.2. Son of man (ſaith the Lord to the Prophet) thou dwelleſt in the midſt of a rebellious houſe, That have eies to ſee, and ſee not, they have ears to hear, and hear not. Their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion being demonſtrated from this ground, That they have eies, and ſee not, <hi>&amp;c. (i.e.)</hi> they know and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand how to perform their duty, but they will not do it; according to that in <hi>Chap.</hi> 33.31, 32. He that knoweth to do well, and doth not, to him it is ſin, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4 17. Whereas that which a man underſtandeth not, nor is any waies able to perform, is imputed to his infirmity only, which God will never lay to his charge, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.2. For we have an high-Prieſt that can have compaſſion on the ignorant, and of thoſe that are out of the way; I obtained mercy, becauſe I did it ignorantly, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:119970:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> That the opinion of enforcing Faith and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance in men, cannot ſtand with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the laſt Judgement by Chriſt.</head>
               <p>THis Doctrine (namely of Gods neceſſitating re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in men) is inconſiſtent with the laſt ſentence of Chriſt, (which as the Scriptures declare) ſhal be according to every mans works; And therfore foraſmuch as al ſuch things wherunto men are enforced by a power which they cannot reſiſt, are imputable only unto that power whereby they are ſo enforced: It muſt follow that if that ſome men ſhould by God be neceſſitated to repentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they could be no more juſtified according to the ſentence of Chriſt in relation thereunto, then any other men could be condemned with reference to ſuch evill actions whereunto they were enforced by a power which they could no waies poſſibly reſiſt. To make this evident by the Scriptures, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.27. it's declared by Chriſt himſelf, That when he commeth in the Glory of his Father with his Angels, he will reward every man according to his workes. In like manner, <hi>Revel.</hi> 22.12. he ſaith, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I come quickly, and my reward is with me, to give to every man according as his worke ſhall be; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable unto which is the Teſtimony of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. We muſt all appear before the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119970:30"/>
Seat of Chriſt, that every one may receive the things done in his boby, according to that he hath done, whether it be good or bad. According to which rule, (the Scriptures aforehand deſcribing unto us the manner of the laſt Judgement, as if it were already paſt) we finde the ſentence of Chriſt denounced to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all perſons, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.34. with <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12, 13.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That all ſuch actions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereunto perſons are enforced againſt the choice and aſſent of their own wils, are not imputed unto them as their own actions, will plainly appear; firſt, by <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.25, 26. If a man ſaith the Text, finde a betrothed Damſell in the field, and force her; then the man only that forced her ſhall die. But unto the Damſell thou ſhalt doe nothing, there is in the Damſell no ſin worthy of death: for as when a man riſeth againſt his neighbour, and ſlayeth him, even ſo is this matter. Likewiſe by the words of the Apoſtle, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.2. If I doe that I would not, it is no more I that doe it, but ſinne that dwelleth in me; from which in the 24, and 25. verſes, he concludeth, That God would acquit him. And thereupon in the 1. verſe of the 8. chapter, declareth unto all, That there is no condemnation belonging unto men for ſuch actions. The reaſon hereof is, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that God looketh only at the heart of a man, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7. and alwaies judgeth of him according to what he obſerveth therein, whether it be good or bad; what is willed and determined therein, he reckoneth it as if it were done, though through want of opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or ability it never be effected: from whence it is that the Apoſtle declareth unto us for a generall rule, in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. That if there be firſt a willing minde, it is accepted according to that a man hath,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119970:31"/>
and not according to that he hath not; which we finde verified unto us by a clear inſtance, in the 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.18.19. of Gods kinde acceptation of <hi>Davids</hi> affection to build him an Houſe, though that it was never built by him, Whereas it was in thy heart (ſaith the Lord) to build me an houſe, thou didſt well, that it was in thine heart; nevertheles, thou ſhalt not build me the Houſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And we may alſo obſerve that <hi>Solomon,</hi> who by Gods appointment did build it, received not a greater reward for his action therein, then <hi>David</hi> did for his affection thereunto: And ſo on the other ſide, Chriſt informeth us, That the things that defile a man, are only thoſe that proceed from his heart, Out of the heart, ſaith he, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.19, 20. proceedeth evil thoughts (he ſpeaketh not of thoſe that are ſuggeſted, or that at unawares ariſe therein, and are forthwith quenched, and ſuppreſſed, for theſe defile no man) but of thoſe that are conceived and harboured therein, which when opportunity ſerveth, break forth into murthers, adulteries, fornications, thefts, falſe witnes, blaſphemies, theſe defile the man; upon which ground it is, That the Scriptures declareth <hi>David</hi> to be a man according to Gods own heart, ſave only in the matter of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 15.5. Wherein deliberately and with purpoſe of heart (as muſt needs be conceived) he choſe the thing which he knew to be evill, which in other caſes (wherein his actions much ſwerved from the rules of perfect juſtice) he did not; and therefore is neither blamed nor accuſed for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> God doth not juſtifie men for Faith, but by Faith: nor reward them for their workes, but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their workes, the reward of good workes being
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119970:31"/>
Grace belonging to Adopted Children, not to ſervants for the worke done.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The diſtinction betwixt Juſtification by Faith, and for Faith, is altogether vaine: ſeeing that he that is juſtified by Faith, or by reaſon thereof, which is all one, is ſo juſtified for Faith: Becauſe that without Faith he cannot pleaſe God, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.5, 6. nor obtain acceptation with him. Thy Faith, ſaith Chriſt to the woman, hath ſaved thee, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.5. The like may be ſaid concerning the diſtinction betwixt reward for workes, and according to workes; in regard that he that is rewarded according to his workes, is ſo rewarded for his workes: as he that is rewarded accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as he hath fed, relieved, and feaſted the poor, that were not able to feaſt him again, (as Chriſt hath promiſed in <hi>Luke</hi> 14.13, 14.) or as he that is reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according as he hath given a cup of cold water in the name of Chriſt, (having no better in his power to give) he is ſo rewarded for that he hath ſo done, by reaſon that otherwiſe he ſhould have received no ſuch reward.</p>
               <p>And yet it is not to be denied but that Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through Faith, and reward of good workes, ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally proceedeth from the meer Grace and ſpeciall favour of God in Jeſus Chriſt, conſidering that by the Law we can lay claim unto no ſuch thing, but muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our ſelves, according to that Covenant, guilty of everlaſting death, or the diſſolution of our natures for ever in the Grave; and therefore whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we either doe or ſhall receive from God more or leſſe than this, as our preſent being in this life, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of the Creatures, a time of repentance, with the means thereof, as redemption from the curſe of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119970:32"/>
the Law, Reſurrection to another life, Adoption and Salvation through Faith, or conformity to the will of God, known and underſtood by us; muſt be attributed to the alone Grace of God in Jeſus Chriſt, through whom he hath obtained theſe things for us, and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted and granted to beſtow there upon us. Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to which diſtinction betwixt the Covenants, is that diſtinction which runneth through the Rodie of the New-Teſtament, betwixt righteouſnes and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, workes and workes, reward and reward, to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood according to the firſt covenant, There is none that doth good, none righteous, but all have ſinned and are fallen ſhort of the Glory of God, accurſed, dead and excluded from all happineſſe for ever. But in relation to the ſecond Covenant made with us in Chriſt, as we were conſidered in this eſtate; we are through his death and reſurrection redeemed from death, made alive from the dead, under a Law of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſutable to our frailty, and capable of working righteouſneſſe thereby, under the promiſes of Adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of reward of good workes, and of raigning toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with God and Chriſt for ever and ever. It doth not therefore follow, That becauſe men obtain Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Adoption through Faith, and are rewarded for their good workes, that therefore all theſe things are not obtained through Grace; ſeeing that it is from the unſpeakable Grace of God, that we who were dead doe live, that we enjoy ſuch precious promiſes, and upon ſuch gracious termes, whereby we are or may be made partakers of them.</p>
               <p>And yet although that Juſtification and Salvation, are thus founded upon the Grace of God, yet hath eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man through the performance of thoſe things
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119970:32"/>
whereunto the ſame is promiſed as juſt, a right and claime thereunto, as our firſt Father <hi>Adam</hi> could have had unto life by obedience to the Law, as the words of the Apoſtle in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.10. doe plainly witneſſe, God is not unfaithfull (ſaith he) to forget your worke and labour, of love, the righteouſneſſe of God is engaged to performe whatſoever, forth of his goodneſſe he hath promiſed.</p>
               <p>And as for the pretence of ſome (gathered from theſe and ſuch like Scriptures, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10, 11. <hi>Luke</hi> 27.) That Salvation is freely beſtowed upon men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any thing required on their part thereunto; their miſtake therein is clearly diſcovered from theſe grounds.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the Apoſtles of Jeſus Chriſt who handled not the Word of God deceitfully, but commended themſelves to every mans conſcience, as in the ſight of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. doe every where in Anſwer to the Queſtion, What men ſhould doe to be ſaved? De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, That men muſt repent and believe, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37, 38. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.30, 31.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From the practice of the Apoſtles themſelves, who being fully inſtructed in the knowledge of the Grace of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.27. yet ſtrove to obtain the Crown of eternall life, And not un-neceſſarily, as men beating the Aire, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.25, 26, 27. with 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5.12.</p>
               <p n="3">3. From the tenure of the promiſes, which all runne conditionally; I will give to him that is a thirſt of the water of life freely, <hi>Rom.</hi> 20.6. Be thou Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full unto death, and I will give thee a Crown of life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.10. I have fought a good fight, I have finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my courſe, I have kept the Faith, henceforth there
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119970:33"/>
is laid up for me a Crown of righteouſneſſe, which the Lord the righteous Judge will give me at that day, and not to me only, but unto all thoſe that love his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6, 7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.24.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And laſtly, from hence that Salvation it ſelf is intituled, The inheritance of reward, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.24. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as reward doth alwaies preſuppoſe ſomething either done or to be done, in recompence whereof, the ſame is given. <hi>Moſes</hi> choſe to ſuffer with the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, becauſe he had reſpect to the recompence of reward, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.25, 26.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And although in 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10, 11. It is ſaid that God hath given us eternall life; yet in verſ. the 12. it is alſo ſaid, That this life is in his Son, and that he that hath it muſt have the Son. And the ſame Apoſtle in his 2 Epiſt. v. 9, plainly declareth, That whoſoever tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſeth and abideth not in the doctrine of Chriſt, hath neither the Father nor the Son; He is the author of Salvation to thoſe that obey him, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 5.9.</p>
               <p>And as for <hi>Luke</hi> 1.77. where it is propheſied, That <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt ſhould give knowledge of Salvation to the Jewes, by the remiſſion of ſinnes. The meaning thereof is beſt interpreted by the tenour of his own preaching unto them; whereby they are taught not to expect either remiſſion of ſins, or Salvation otherwiſe then through repentance, and amendment of life, <hi>Luk.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.8. according to that in <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Faith being the gift of God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. Salvation in reference whereunto it is given, is the gift of God alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, It is not clear in this Text that the Apoſtle doth intend Faith to be the gift of God; but
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119970:33"/>
rather that ſalvation is the gift of God, and in what nature Salation is given by him, hath been ſhewed before.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But admit that Faith is the gift of God; it doth not therefore follow, that Faith whereunto Salvation is promiſed is the gift of God; for Faith in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures is diverſly taken: As firſt, it is taken for the Doctrine of Faith; in which reſpect, they that have preached the ſame, are ſaid to preach the Faith, <hi>Galat.</hi> 1.23. and thoſe to whom it was preached, are ſaid to hear the Faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.5. and thoſe that received and ſubjected themſelves thereunto, are ſaid to be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the Faith, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.7. Secondly, it is taken for the bare credence and belief of the Doctrine of Chriſt; in which reſpect, The Rulers that loved the praiſe of men more than the praiſe of God, are ſaid to believe in Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 12.42, 43. And thus the Devils are alſo ſaid to believe and tremble, <hi>James</hi> 2.19. Thirdly It is taken for the knowledge, love and obedience of the Doctrine of Chriſt; In which reſpect, thoſe that have departed from the love and obedience thereof, are ſaid to make Shipwrack of Faith and a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19. And laſtly, it is taken for an aſſured hope and expectation of eternall life: begotten in men through a conſcientious privity of the truth of their repentance, ſincerity of their obedience, and the gracious promiſes of God made thereunto (according as the words of the Apoſtle, in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8. before rehearſed do declare.) Now although that Faith in the firſt and ſecond acceptation; whereunto the Apoſtle in theſe words, <hi>(viz.)</hi> (It is the gift of God) may have reſpect) be acknowledged the gift of God, and be after a ſort neceſſarily impoſed upon men (eſpecially when
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119970:34"/>
as the Doctrine of Chriſt is clearly and evidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated unto them (by the miraculous power of God, as it was by the Miniſtery of the Apoſtles.) Yet in the third acceptation, by which alone men are inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled to Salvation, it cannot from hence be concluded to be the gift of God; it being begotten in men only through a due and ſerious conſideration of the truth, certainty, worth, and excellency of the Doctrine ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of diſcovered unto them: For like as a ſoft anſwer turneth away wrath, and a ſoft tongue breaketh the bone, (according to <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.1. and 25.15.) Even ſo the unſpeakable love and goodneſſe of God appearing unto men, received into, and laid up in their hearts, (as it is required in <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.6, 11, 18. <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.4.) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth in them a love towards God, obedience to his Word, crucifieth them to the world, caſteth downe imaginations and every high thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God, and bringeth into captivity every thought, to the obedience of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4, 5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.16, 17. From whence it is that thoſe perſons who have had the mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God demonſtrated unto them (in a more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant meaſure than others) and have not thereby been ſubdued to the love and obedience of him, are charged with forgetting God their Saviour and maker, with forgetting his workes, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 106.21, 13. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.18. With forgetting that they were purged from their old ſinnes, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9. Are called forgetfull hearers of the word, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.25. and reſembled to a man beholding his naturall face in a glaſſe, and ſtraight way forgetteth what manner of man he was, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.23, 24. plainly arguing that the conſideration of the love and goodneſſe of God towards men, is the only
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119970:34"/>
and effectual means to beget the love and obedience of God in them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But let it be granted, That the Apoſtle in theſe words doth conclude, that faith whereunto Salvation is given, is the gift of God, yet it will not from thence follow, That it is by him neceſſarily begotten or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced in any men.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe that in the Scriptures, that is declared to be given, which is only offered to mens acceptation to receive or refuſe, as themſelves ſhall pleaſe: So <hi>Ephron</hi> the <hi>Hittire</hi> gave the field of <hi>Machpelah,</hi> and the Cave that was therein to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 23.11. And the ſouldiers that crucified Chriſt, gave him to drink wine mingled with myrrhe, but neither the one nor the other of them, were thereby poſſeſſed with that which was ſo given unto them, becauſe they refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to accept thereof, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 23.12, 13, 17. <hi>Mark</hi> 15.23.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That in the Scriptures is ſaid to be given by God unto men, which is no otherwiſe obtained, then through a free, voluntary uſe and improvement of ſuch means, which he hath vouchſafed unto them for thoſe ends. Theſe are the children, ſaith <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 33.5. which God hath graciouſly given unto thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, he giveth food to all fleſh. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.25. He gave the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> their corn, and their wine, and multiplied their ſilver and their gold, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.8. He gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth us (ſaith the Apoſtle) richly all things to enioy, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17. And thus God hath given eternal life to all men in his Son, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.10, 11. So God being ſaid to give faith unto men, when he only affordeth unto them the means thereof, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.31. That faith which is obtained by the uſe of that means, muſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119970:35"/>
needs be acknowledged to be his gift alſo. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as the Scriptures teſtimony, that ſalvation is of grace, and the gift of God, is no ſufficient evidence to prove, that therefore it is conferred upon men any otherwiſe then in the nature of a reward and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of their obedience, repentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the Scriptures evidence, That faith is the gift of God, a ſufficient ground to prove, that therefore it is either infuſed into mens hearts by the Spirit of God, or intruded upon them by the irreſiſtable ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration thereof, or that it is any otherwiſe obtained by them, then through the voluntary uſe and improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the means that God hath vouchſafed unto them for that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>It is declared, That God gave the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> bread from heaven, and fed them thereby, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.25. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.31. <hi>Deut.</hi> 8.3. And yet none will from thence affirm, That he either inſpired them therewith, or enforced them to eat thereof, or that their ſuſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereby, did not wholly depend upon their own voluntary gathering and applying the ſame thereunto, according as the Lord commanded, <hi>Exodus</hi> 16.16. <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.8.</p>
               <p>To conclude therefore this Argument ſeeing (as it was ſhewed before) that God only regardeth the hearts of men. And that his love and diſpleaſure is directed towards them, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that which he obſerveth to be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen or refuſed therein, vertue and vice, life and death proceeding from thence,<note n="*" place="margin">Life and death is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid to be in the power of the tongue, <hi>Prov. 18.21.</hi> And that by our words we ſhall be juſtified, and by our words we ſhall be condemned, <hi>Mat. 12.37.</hi> becauſe that the tongue is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſed to be the infallible In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter of the heart, and that nothing is uttered by the one, which is not firſt choſen, and determined in the other, <hi>Mat. 12.34.</hi> which plainly argueth, That all vertue and vice pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from thence, and that every mans judgement in the day of Chriſt, ſhall be, not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſuch thoughts or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions whereunto they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced, but according to that which was freely choſen, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced and accepted by them in their own hearts.</note> 
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119970:35"/>
23. If that faith and repentance did not proceed from the free and voluntary choice of mans will, as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in the ſight of God he ſhould not be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from the impenitent and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient; ſo neither ſhould he finde any favour or acceptation with God by reaſon thereof, or receive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reward from him at the laſt day for the ſame. If I doe this thing willingly (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) I have a reward, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.17. but otherwiſe not, as his words doe clearly imply.</p>
               <p>And therefore to the end that all men may obtain eternal life, life and death being by Almighty God ſet before them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.19. it concerneth them to heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en diligently to wiſdoms voice, calling upon them to chooſe the fear of the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.29. And from a thankfull apprehenſion of his goodneſſe diſcovered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, with uprightneſſe of heart to apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the obedience of him; and that whatſoever they doe, to doe it willingly, and not grudgingly, nor of neceſſity, knowing that he only loveth the chearfull giver: from whence the widdows mite, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing offered with affection, becometh a moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſacrifice unto him. He deſireth not to reap, where
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119970:36"/>
he hath not firſt ſowed, yet he expecteth from us, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the talents delivered unto us, the which therefore every man ought faithfully to improve. And in ſo doing, when the Lord ſhall return to take an account of his ſervants, he may aſſuredly conclude, That he will graciouſly imbrace and receive him with this heavenly Eulogy, Well done good and faithfull ſervant, enter thou into the joy of thy Lord, when the wicked and ſlothfull ſervant ſhall be caſt into outer darkneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Serveth for the clearing of ſuch Texts of Scripture, which ſeem to imply a diſability in men to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the means vouchſafed unto them, for their ſalvation.</head>
               <p>AGainſt that which hath been ſaid there are two main Objections, which require ſome further Anſwer to be given unto them; The firſt of which is grounded upon ſuch Scriptures which ſeem to imply a diſability in men to improve the means vouchſafed to their ſalvation: The ſecond is grounded upon ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scriptures which ſeem to import repentance, faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be neceſſitated in men by the irreſiſtable pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God.</p>
               <p>The Scriptures appertaining to the firſt of theſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections are theſe and ſuch like, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. <hi>John</hi> 6.44. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. which in order I ſhall
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119970:36"/>
endeavour to clear, and ſo proceed to thoſe which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the ſecond.</p>
               <p n="1">1. From the firſt of theſe <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. the words whereof are as followeth (And you hath he quickned who were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins. Where in times paſt ye walked, according to the courſe of this world, according to the prince of the power of the air, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> fulfilling the luſts of the fleſh, and of the minde, and were by nature the children of wrath) Its conceived that a man deprived of his natural life, is not more incapable of performing the actions of living men then a man in his natural condition, is of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming any thing required of him to his Salvation. Which will appear very incredible, if that we doe but conſider, that the Scriptures doe evidently declare, that God requireth not of any men, but according to the talents delivered unto them, he requireth not five, where he giveth but two, nor two, where he giveth but one, nor yet one, where he hath not vouchſafed any: If ye were blinde (ſaith Chriſt) ye had not ſin, <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.41.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Therefore ſecondly, I anſwer, That although that this text doth declare, that the <hi>Epheſians</hi> were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins: yet it doth not argue that they were neceſſarily dead therein, or that they might not have avoided the ſame, for mens being bad is no good ground to prove that they could not be good. If that they were neceſſarily ſuch, it muſt be either by reaſon that they were ſuch by birth, or elſe through want of inſtruction, but that they were ſuch by birth, cannot be gathered from this text.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe that thoſe ſins and treſpaſſes, wherein they are ſaid to be dead, are declared to be ſuch, as
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119970:37"/>
relate to their converſation, and time of ripe age, they walked according to the courſe of this world, the prince that ruleth in the air, fulfilled the deſires of the minde, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is not incident to the eſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It was obſerved before, That all ſins have their original in the wils of men; and then foraſmuch as children cannot diſtinguiſh betwixt good and evil, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.39. they cannot poſſibly chooſe the thing that is evil; and therefore cannot be guilty thereof, much leſſe dead therein.</p>
               <p>If it be objected, That they are ſaid to be the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath by nature.</p>
               <p>Its anſwered, That by nature in this place probably may be underſtood that fleſhly, ſenſuall or deviliſh courſe of life, wherein they had their converſation (for ſo the word naturall in the 3. Chapter of <hi>Iames</hi> the 15. verſe, compared with the margent, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be rendered) in reference unto which, they may here be ſaid, to be children of wrath: But if that thereby we muſt underſtand their eſtate by birth, then in that reſpect are they to be eſteemed none otherwiſe the children of wrath, then as they were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the wrath or curſe of mortality, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures by their deſcent from <hi>Adam</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">By wrath in this place cannot poſſibly be underſtood the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of hell, becauſe that puniſhment relates to the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which could not have been had not Chriſt died and roſe again; and therefore the curſe of the fall (of which on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we are chargeable by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) muſt of neceſſity end in the grave, and the being of fallen <hi>Adam,</hi> there ceaſing, no puniſhment beyond the ſame can be inflicted. And therefore the wrath or condemnation of hell muſt of neceſſity be proper to the being that is to come, and the reward of diſobedience in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and not of our fall in the firſt <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </note>. From whence being ranſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the death and reſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt, the more to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119970:37"/>
endear them unto him for his goodneſſe towards them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the Apoſtle in this place may put them in minde thereof.</p>
               <p>And as they were not dead in treſpaſſes and ſins by birth: So neither were they dead therein through want of divine illumination or demonſtration (though that neither the Moſaical Law, Doctrine of the Prophets, or of Chriſt, were delivered unto them) as appeareth by <hi>Act.</hi> 14.17. where we reade that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> having before reproved the men of <hi>Lyſtra,</hi> for walking after ſtrange gods, and ſacrificing unto them (to convince them, and diſcover to us, that it was not through want of divine evidence that they ſo walked) They declare, that God did not leave himſelf without witneſſe, that he only ought to have been worſhipped by them, in that he did them good, and gave them rain from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, filling their hearts with food and gladneſſe: and the ſame Apoſtle further declareth, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.19. That that which may be known of God was manifeſt unto them (to wit the <hi>Gentiles</hi>) for God ſhewed it unto them: For the inviſible things of him (ſaith he) from the Creation of the world, are clearly ſeen, being underſtood by the things that are made, even his eternal power and Godhead.</p>
               <p>And yet the more fully to evidence this truth, in <hi>verſ.</hi> 21, it's plainly declared, that by the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid means they did attain to the knowledge of God,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119970:38"/>
and of that worſhip that he required of them, when they knew God, ſaith the text, they glorified him, not as God, neither were thankfull, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the judgement of God, that they which did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch things, were worthy of death, did not only doe the ſame, but took pleaſure in thoſe that did them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 32. And thereupon in <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.1, 3. are declared to be without excuſe, both in their diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and condemnation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This is yet more clearly demonſtrated by the words of the Apoſtle, in <hi>Chap.</hi> 2.14, 15. When the Gentiles (ſaith he) which have not the Law, doe by nature the things contained in the Law: theſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not the Law are a Law unto themſelves, which ſheweth the work of the Law written in their hearts; their conſciences alſo bearing them witneſſe, and their thoughts in the mean while accuſing and excuſing one another in the day, when God ſhall judge the ſecrets of men by Ieſus Chriſt. In which words theſe two things are plainly declared; Firſt, That whatſoever was neceſſarily required of them to their ſalvation, was fully known unto them. Secondly, That the things ſo known by them, was within their power to perform and practiſe. That their duty was fully knowne unto them, he demonſtrateth from theſe two grounds.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That ſome of them did performe the ſame, which according as he argueth, they could not have done, had they been ignorant thereof, when the Gentiles (ſaith he) doe by nature the things contained in the Law; they ſhew thereby, that they have the worke of the written in their hearts.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:119970:38"/>2. From hence <hi>(viz.)</hi> that thoſe of them which did not performe the things required of them to their Salvation, had therein conſciences accuſing them at preſent (and ſhould accuſe them) by reaſon thereof, in the day when God ſhal judge the ſecrets of men by Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; the which ſhould be impoſſible, were not the ſame things known and underſtood by them, as we may perceive by a very plain inſtance, in <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. where we read, That <hi>Abimelech</hi> having taken unto him <hi>Abrahams</hi> Wife, upon his denying her to be his Wife, and of Gods threatning him with death, in caſe that he did not reſtore her again unto him, he not being privy to himſelf of any evil committed therein; In verſ. the 4. and 5. thus replieth in his own defence, Lord wilt thou alſo ſlay a righteous Nation? Said he not unto me ſhe is my ſiſter? And ſhe, even ſhe her ſelf ſaid, He is my brother; in the integrity of my heart and innocency of my hands I have done this; the which grounds alſo ſerve plainly to demonſtrate the truth of the later poſition, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That whatſoever was required of them to their Salvation, was within their power to be performed by them. For by the ſame reaſon that ſome performed them by nature; others in the ſame condition might have done ſo likewiſe, and conſciouſneſſe that they could not performe them, being known unto them, would quiet their mindes both in this world, and at the day of Chriſt, as much as conſciouſneſſe of their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance thereof could. For the conſcience of a man in the omiſſion or miſdoing of his duty not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, acquitteth him therein only upon this ground, That the doing or right performance thereof was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible unto him, notwithſtanding his utmoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119970:39"/>
the which ground of impoſſibility, to performe his duty will appeaſe his conſcience in the omiſſion thereof, in any other caſe whatſoever. And thus this Objection with the ground thereof is taken away.</p>
               <p>The ſecond text is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. the words whereof are theſe: But the naturall man perceiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſhnes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, neither can he know them becauſe they are Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually diſcerned; from whence it is ſuppoſed that no man in the eſtate of nature, not endued with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, can poſſibly underſtand or doe any thing required of him to his Salvation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The groundleſneſſe of this ſuppoſition was clearly diſproved before, by the teſtimony of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, concerning the Gentiles, their doing by nature the things required of them to their Iuſtification and Salvation.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But yet the more fully to take away the ground thereof. By the things of the Spirit in this place muſt needs be underſtood, either ſuch things which are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the Spirits revelation to thoſe which after their believing have received the ſame, according to <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.12. where Chriſt telleth his Diſciples, That he had many things to ſay unto them, which they could not then (<hi>viz.</hi> before the Spirit was given unto them) bear: How be it (ſaith he) the Spirit of Truth when he is come, he will guide you into all Truth, and will ſhew you things to come. Or elſe ſecondly, By the things of the Spirit muſt be underſtood the Doctrine of the Goſpel in generall, mentioned chap. 1.17, 18.21.2.4.5. By the wiſdome of the World is accounted fooliſhneſſe. If that the things of the Spirit be taken in the firſt acceptation, (as may be conceived from the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119970:39"/>
12, and 13, verſes, where the Apoſtle intimateth, that the things whereof he here ſpeaketh, were none other then what was revealed or taught unto himſelf and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by the Spirit which they had received) then this text pretendeth not at all to prove, that men in the eſtate of nature cannot perceive or doe any thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of them to their Salvation, but only that none can underſtand the myſteries or ſecrets of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, untill firſt they believe the Goſpel, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.11. and are Baptized with the Holy Ghoſt; which the World cannot receive, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.17. Nor yet ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, If that by the things of the Spirit are under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Doctrine of the Goſpel in general: it will not thereupon follow, that a man in the eſtate of nature, by the exerciſe of his underſtanding, cannot perceive or receive the knowledge thereof, when it is plainly preached, and by the evidence of the Spirit demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto him. Seeing it is manifeſt by the Scriptures, that the very worſt of naturall men, The Rulers, Scribes and Phariſees, have attained to the knowledge of the moſt fundamentall points of Chriſtianity; under which the whole Doctrine therof is comprehended. As 1 They believed that there was a God. 2. They believ that Jeſus Chriſt was the Meſſias and Saviour of the World, and ſo conſequently that his whole Doctrine was none other then the undoubted Oracles of God, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.23, 24, 25. <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.42, 43. And thirdly, They believed the reſurrection of the juſt and of the unjuſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 23.7, 9. <hi>Acts</hi> 24.15. And the Goſpel being thus underſtood by men, they are thereby ſufficiently enabled to the obedience thereof; whence it is that the Scriptures unto ſuch perſons ſpeaketh on this wiſe, Receive not the grace of God in vain; having
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119970:40"/>
theſe promiſes, let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of fleſh and ſpirit, and perfect holineſſe in the fear of God: He that knoweth to do wel, and doth not, or that knoweth his maſters wil, and doth it not, to him it is ſin, and he ſhall be beaten with many ſtripes. Such manner of ſpeech alwaies preſuppoſing an ability in the perſons to whom it is directed to improve the ſame to the end thereof.</p>
               <p>Wherefore we are not to conceive (that becauſe it is ſaid, The naturall man perceiveth not the things of the ſpirit, nor can receive them) that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no man deſtitute of the ſpirit can poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly underſtand or give obedience to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt, when it is evidently (in the preaching thereof) demonſtrated unto them. But we are thereby given to know, That no man whatſoever meaſuring the Goſpel of Grace, teaching him to deny al ungodlines &amp; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſt, &amp; to live right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſly, ſoberly &amp; godly in this preſent world, <hi>&amp;c. Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12.) by the natural, earthly &amp; ſenſual principles and wiſdom of the world.<note n="*" place="margin">S. <hi>John</hi> in his <hi>1 Joh. 2.15.</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting not to love the world, nor the things that are therein, in ver. <hi>16,</hi> teacheth us, what he would have us to underſtand thereby (viz.) the luſts of the fleſh, the luſts of the eyes, and the pride of life; whereby we are alſo taught to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, whereunto the wiſdome of the world, ſo often ſpoken of in the firſt, ſecond and third Chap. of the <hi>1 Cor.</hi> is to be confined (<hi>viz.</hi>) to the promoting and accompliſhing the fore-ſaid ends, becauſe that it cannot extend beyond it ſelf, or direct men unto any thing that is not comprehended therein, the which may ſerve to admoniſh all men to beware of branding the vertuous and juſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pals, whether of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, or any other perſons whatſoever (though learned in the book of Creation only) with the odious infamy of worldly wiſdom: An evil too ordinary in our times.</note>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:119970:40"/>
(teaching him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny all godlineſſe and goodnes in this world, and to live according to the luſts of the fleſh, the luſts of the eyes, and pride of life, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.16. can poſſibly receive the ſame, and become obedient thereunto, but muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject it as fooliſhneſſe. God and the world, the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, and the wiſdome of the world, being ſo directly oppoſite and contrary each unto other, That whoſoever will love the one, muſt hate the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; or that will embrace the one, muſt reject the other. If any man, ſaith <hi>James,</hi> will be a friend to the world, he muſt be an enemy unto God, <hi>James</hi> 4.4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joſhua</hi> having put it to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> choice, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they would ſerve the Lord, or the gods that their Fathers had worſhipped, <hi>Chap.</hi> 24.15. And they having in anſwer thereunto declared, That they would ſerve the Lord only, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. He replieth unto them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. in theſe words. <hi>(Ye cannot ſerve the Lord)</hi> wherein his meaning is not, that it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for them to ſerve the Lord (for then he would not have put it to their choice, whether they would ſerve him or not) but his meaning is, that they could not ſerve him acceptably, unleſſe they did wholly cleave unto him, and reject Idols, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14.19. So likewiſe in this place, when the Apoſtle ſaith, That this natural man cannot, receive the things of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God (that is to ſay, approve and ſubject him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119970:41"/>
to the wiſdome and inſtruction of God, contained in the doctrine of the Goſpel) we may not ſuppoſe that thereby he concludeth it abſolutely impoſſible for them ſo to do; but impoſſible only ſo long as they retain and nouriſh in themſelves the vicious wiſdome of the world; whereby they are inſtructed to gain-ſay, reſiſt and oppoſe all godlineſſe, vertue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty.</p>
               <p>The third Text, is, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.44. The words whereof are theſe, No man can come unto me, except the Father that ſent me draw him. From whence it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily ſuppoſed, That no man can believe in Jeſus Chriſt, except that he be neceſſarily enforced there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by an immediate exerciſe or operation of the power of God upon his ſoul.</p>
               <p>For anſwer whereunto, I deſire that it may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, that this word <hi>(draw)</hi> whereupon the whole weight of this Objection ſtandeth, is diverſly underſtood in the Scriptures, and is not alwaies ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for a neceſſary compultion, as it is here ſuppoſed, but ordinarily for an argumentative perſwaſion only, as appeareth by <hi>Act.</hi> 5.37. Where (ſpeaking concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one <hi>Judas,</hi> a ſeducer of the people) it is ſaid, That he drew away much people after him. As alſo by the words of the Apoſtle, in <hi>Act.</hi> 20.30. where he declareth to the Church, That from amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves men ſhould ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, and ſhould draw away Diſciples after them. And that God only draweth men to the love of himſelf, the Faith and Obedience of Chriſt, by the diſcovery of his goodneſſe towards them, and of the danger of their ingratitude towards him, doth evidently appear, by theſe following Scriptures, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 11.3, 4. where
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119970:41"/>
(concerning backſliding <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whoſe goodnes like the morning dew paſſed away) the Lord thus ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, I taught <hi>Ephraim</hi> alſo to goe, taking them by their arms, but they know that I healed them, I drew them with cords of a man, with bands of love, and I was to them as one that taketh of the yoke on the jaws, and I laid meat unto them. And in <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.38, 39. The juſt ſhall live by faith; but if any man draw back (ſaith the Lord) my ſoul ſhall have no pleaſure in him. But we are not of thoſe (ſaith the Apoſtle) that draw back to perdition, but of thoſe that believe to the ſaving of their ſoul.</p>
               <p>In which Scriptures are diſcovered (beſides the means whereby God draweth men) theſe two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That God draweth all men, the backſliding, and thoſe that draw back to perdition, as well as thoſe that believe to the ſaving of their ſouls. And</p>
               <p n="2">2. That he ſo draweth none, but that poſſibly they may draw back to perdition (as <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and thoſe others ſuppoſed in the later Text) it being other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to no purpoſe, to preſent men, with the danger of drawing back, nor would it be any matter of commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, either in the Apoſtle, or that number where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he joyneth himſelf, that they did not draw back, as well as others: For what praiſe is it not to draw back, when as it is impoſſible ſo to do.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The words of the Text, compared with the former, and following verſes, doe clearly import, That the drawing of the Father, whereof Chriſt ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, conſiſteth only in external means, and doctrinal inſtruction delivered unto men by his preaching. In verſ. 41. Chriſt declaring himſelf to be the living bread, (or bread of life) come down from heaven, which giveth
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:119970:42"/>
life unto the world, and that by eating thereof, a man ſhould live for ever (of which he had ſpoken before, verſ. 33.35.) And the Jews carnally weighing his words therein, and not conſidering that he ſpake not unto them concerning material bread, wherewith their natural lives ſhould be ſuſtained. In verſ. 41, 42. Murmur againſt him, ſaying, Is not this <hi>Ieſus</hi> the ſon of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> whoſe father and mother vve know? How then ſaith he, I came down from heaven? Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in verſ. 43, 44, 45. Chriſt that he might remove from before them the occaſion of their ſtumbling at him, by reaſon of his parentage, and inſtruct them by vvhat means they ſhould attain to the Belief and Obedience of his Doctrine; anſwereth them to this effect, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that my father and mother be known unto you, yet notwithſtanding, murmur not againſt me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſaid, I am the bread which came down from heaven, to give life unto the vvorld: For it is not my bodies deſcending from heaven, but the promiſed Grace of God touching your Redemption, Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and eternal Salvation thorow my Death, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to my doctrine, which I intend, vvhen I ſo ſpake unto you, the vvhich you cannot receive, except my Father vvhich ſent me, draw you, according as it is vvritten in the Prophets, They ſhall be all taught of God: Every man therefore which hath heard and learned of the Father (<hi>viz.</hi> received his inſtruction, and ſubmitted themſelves thereunto) cometh unto me. And then in verſ. 46. leaſt that he ſhould be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken in vvhat he had here ſaid concerning the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers drawing and teaching, and be thought thereby to affirm, That none could believe him to be the bread of life, &amp; Saviour of the vvorld, except that the Father im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119970:42"/>
in his own perſon, or by his ſpirit ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruct them therein, &amp; enforce them thereunto. He ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyneth theſe vvords, Not that any man hath ſeen the Father at any time, ſave he that is of God, he hath ſeen the Father; intimating thereby; That although that the Father teacheth men, yet he teacheth them not perſonally or immediately, but mediately by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery of his Sonne, vvho is God vvith us, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.23. and ſent into the vvorld, to the end, that we may be taught of God by him, according to theſe plain Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.16. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.49, 50. So that when it is ſaid, That none can come unto Chriſt, except that he be drawn thereunto by the teaching of the Father; The meaning thereof is only this, That no man can receive Jeſus Chriſt to be the Saviour of the vvorld, and become obedient unto him, except that he hear and learn, be drawn and perſwaded thereto by the inſtruction of the Father, in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of his Son.</p>
               <p>The fourth Text alleadged to prove men incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of improving the means of ſalvation, is, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. The words whereof are theſe, Not that we are ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of our ſelves to think any thing, as of our ſelves, but our ſufficiency is of God.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To which I anſwer, firſt, That this Scripture is leaſt of all to the purpoſe for which it is alleadged, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it is not pleaded, that of our ſelves, as of our ſelves, or as we are men ſimply conſidered, without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther having the Law vvritten in our hearts, or ſome diſcovery made unto us of our deliverance from mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality and happineſſe in the vvorld to come, to thinke any good thought, either towards God, or of reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves according to the rules of vertue or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119970:43"/>
It being according to the teſtimony of the Apoſtle, if that the dead vvere not raiſed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently no felicity to be expected after death, our only vviſdome to eat and drink, to free and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit our ſelves from all manner of troubles and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings vvhatſoever in this vvorld (as for conſcience ſake) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32. with the 19.31, 32. To fill our ſelves with coſtly wine and ointments, and to let no flower of the ſpring paſſe by us, to crown our ſelves vvith Roſe-buds, before they be vvithered, and to leave tokens of our joyfulneſſe in every place, it being our portion and only lot, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 2.7, 8, 9. Its thorow Faith only in the Reſurrection and eternal Salvation, that we overcome the vvorld, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.4. The croſſe of Chriſt crucifieth us to the vvorld, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14. The bloud of Chriſt, or the bloud of the Covenant ſanctifieth us in the world, <hi>Heb.</hi> 16.29. And vve love God, and keep his Commandments, becauſe he hath commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his love unto us, by ſending his Son into the world, that we might live thorow him, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.19. with v. 9, 10. &amp; cap. 5.3.</p>
               <p>But the intent of the Apoſtle in this place doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly appear to be only this <hi>(viz.)</hi> That neither he himſelf, nor any other of the Apoſtles vvere of themſelves, ſufficient to think or conceive that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Miniſtery that was committed unto them. For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the 3. verſe declared, That the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were the Epiſtle of Chriſt miniſtred by them, not written with inke, but with the Spirit of God, not in tables of ſtone, but in fleſhly tables of their hearts, leaſt that they ſhould think of them, above that which vvas meet, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. And aſcribe the honour of this miniſtration unto them, as if that they
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119970:43"/>
had not received it, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6, 7. In the fifth and ſixth verſes, he addeth theſe vvords, Not that vve are ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing, as of our ſelves, but our ſufficiency is of God, who hath made us able Miniſters of the new Teſtament, not of the letter, but of the ſpirit. And therefore in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1. deſireth, that they ſhould account of them only, as Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Stewards of theſe things.</p>
               <p>So that all that can rationally be inferr'd from hence, is only this, That like as the Apoſtles of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves vvere not ſufficient to conceive that Miniſterie, that vvas given unto them, nor to accompliſh any ſuch things, as vvere effected in men thereby: So neither are any men ſufficient of themſelves to conceive or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the things declared therein, or to purifie their hearts thereby, unleſſe that the ſame be revealed unto them: Faith herein (and the effects thereof) being by hearing, and hearing by the vvord of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17.</p>
               <p>Some other Scriptures there are of this nature, but the anſwers to theſe duly conſidered, may be ſufficient to enlighten any indifferent mans underſtanding ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And therefore I ſhall proceed to anſwer to the ſecond main Objection, and to ſuch principal Scriptures vvhich belong thereunto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:119970:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Containing ſeverall Anſwers for the clearing of ſuch Scriptures, which ſeem to import faith to be neceſsitated in men by the irreſistable power of God.</head>
               <p>THe Scriptures alleadged in favour of the ſecond main Objection, are ſuch as theſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28, 29, 30. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.19. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.5, 6. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33.</p>
               <p n="1">1. From the firſt of which, the words whereof are theſe (And we know that all things work together for good to them that love God, to them who are the choſen according to his purpoſe; for whom he did fore-know, he alſo did predeſtinate to be conformed to the Image of his Sonne; Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, whom he did predeſtinate, them he alſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and whom he called, them he juſtified, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) Its conceived that of man-kinde fallen in <hi>Adam,</hi> God in that eſtate before the world, choſe a certain number thereof unto himſelf for his ſons and daughters. And that in reference thereunto in time begetteth them to faith, in his Son juſtifieth them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. To which I anſwer, firſt, That none are choſen to Adoption or Salvation before the world, otherwiſe then in relation to their obedience to thoſe duties which God in the Scriptures by Ieſus Chriſt, and his Apoſtles requireth of men unto thoſe ends, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.9.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119970:44"/>
with the 10. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1, 2. with the 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, The Scriptures doe poſitively declare, That election is only in Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.5. with the 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.13. God hath choſen you to Salvation from the beginning, through ſanctification and belief of the truth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If that God ſhould chooſe men to Adoption and Salvation before the world, otherwiſe then in relation to their obedience to his will made known unto them, Then the will of God in this reſpect, ſhould be two-fold, and contradictions in it ſelf; The one whereby he chooſeth and accepteth to Adoption and Salvation, the wicked, diſobedient and impenitent: The other whereby he will not chooſe, nor receive to adoption or Salvation, any other then the godly, <hi>Philip.</hi> 4.3. the rich in faith, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.5. The penitent, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17, 18. And obedient, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. the third to the fourteenth, which contradiction is impoſſible to be in God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Nor doth the words of the Text prove the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; Wherein firſt is laid down the happy eſtate of thoſe that are called according to purpoſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 28. And 2. the ground thereof, which in <hi>ver.</hi> 29. is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be this <hi>(viz.)</hi> That all thoſe whom God fore-knew (that is to ſay before the world beheld in his Sonne through obedience unto him, who are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in verſe the 28. deſcribed to be ſuch as love God, leaſt that we ſhould conceive that God knew the workers of iniquity before time, whom he refuſeth to own or know in time, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.23.) thoſe he predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, that they ſhould be conformable to the Image of his Sonne in glory, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.21. For the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment whereof he adminiſtreth unto them the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119970:45"/>
means for their calling, and upon their obedience thereunto, receiveth them to juſtification, and in the end to glory.</p>
               <p>The ſecond text is, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.13. the words are theſe: For it is God that worketh in you both to will and to doe of his good pleaſure. From whence it is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, That whatſoever any man willeth or doth accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able unto God and tending to his Salvation, he is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily enforced thereunto by God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> For the removall whereof its to be obſerved, That in the Scriptures things are apprehended unto God, as done by him upon ſeverall grounds: As</p>
               <p n="1">1. Such things are ſaid to be done by him, which he only ſuffereth, or permitteth to be done, <hi>Job</hi> 1.12-21. whether by men or devils, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.15, 16, 17, 21. <hi>Job.</hi> 2.7. with the 10.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Such things are ſaid to be done by him, which are no otherwiſe effected, or brought to paſſe, then by the uſe and improvement of the means that he afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for the doing thereof. Thus he giveth man day by day his daily bread; and feedeth the young ravens that cry, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 147.9.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Alſo ſuch things are ſaid to be done by him, which he affordeth fit and neceſſary means unto men for the doing of: Although that through their neglect or abuſe of thoſe means the ſame he never accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.13. becauſe I have purged thee, and thou waſt not purged; therefore thou ſhalt not be purged from thy filthines, untill I have cauſed my fury to reſt upon thee.</p>
               <p>And that God in this ſenſe only is ſaid to work in the <hi>Philippians,</hi> to will and to doe, plainly appeareth by comparing the 12. verſe with the 13. where the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:119970:45"/>
ſame perſons are required, to work out their own ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation with fear and trembling, becauſe that God worketh in them, <hi>&amp;c</hi> whereby his working in them, to will and to doe, is neceſſarily implied, to conſiſt only in providing and propounding prompt and fit means to induce and perſwade them to will, and to do the things, that in the former verſe is required of them, becauſe that otherwiſe the Argument which the Apoſtle uſeth to ſtirre them up, to work out their ſalvation with fear and trembling, ſhould more fitly ſerve to perſwade them to ſit ſtill and doe nothing, nor take any thought or care at all for that purpoſe. For if that God did work in them the will and the deed, which is all that is neceſſary to ſalvation, there ſhould then remain nothing at all on their part to be done thereunto. So that the words of the Apoſtle in this place, are to be underſtood only; as if he ſhould have ſaid, Be you di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and carefull to performe the things that God requireth of you to your Salvation<note n="*" place="margin">God wrought in the Phariſees and Lawyers, to will and to do, the things required of them to their Salvation, by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of <hi>John:</hi> or elſe in reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the ſame, they could not be charged with fruſtrating and rejecting the counſel of God within themſelves, <hi>Luke 7.30.</hi> with the margent.</note>; for he (is not wanting, but) affordeth unto you al neceſſary means to enable you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And this may alſo ſerve to enlighten us in the underſtanding of <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. (which is the next Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to be anſwered) the words whereof are theſe: For unto you it is given in the behalf of Chriſt, not
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119970:46"/>
only to believe on him, but alſo to ſuffer for his ſake; being delivered in the very ſame nature as the former, <hi>(viz.)</hi> as a ground to perſwade the Philippians to ſtand faſt in the Spirit with one minde, ſtriving together for the Faith of the Goſpel, and in nothing to be terrified by their adverſaries. Foraſmuch as that which is made the ground of an exortation, muſt not only admit, but alſo with ſome kinde of vehemency, ſtirre up and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke to induſtry and diligence for the obtaining of whatſoever is from thence urged, preſſed or perſwaded unto. And that the preſence and aſſured poſſeſſion of a thing doth prohibite a man to ſeeke and endeavour after the ſame, and any other to exhort him therunto; therefore the giving of Faith and perſeverance in this place muſt not be conceived to conſiſt in the actuall conveiance thereof, but in the giving of ſuch means and helps, through the uſe and well improvement whereof, they might be enabled to believe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving to perſevere therein, to the end, againſt all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition whatſoever: becauſe that otherwiſe, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle muſt be underſtood to exhort them to ſtrive for what they already have, or elſe to keep what they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not looſe, yea to ſtrive for them, becauſe that they have theſe things already and cannot looſe them, which is moſt abſurd, and not to be imagined: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as God is ſaid to give food unto all fleſh, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 136.25. By affording unto them means for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining thereof, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.4. <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.4.</p>
               <p>And as he is ſaid to give aſſurance (or faith) unto all men (as touching the reſurrection and judgement to come by Jeſus Chriſt) by his meer granting unto them a ground for their aſſurance therein, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.3. Even ſo in this place God is ſaid to give unto the Philippians
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119970:46"/>
to believe in Chriſt, and to ſuffer for his ſake, by affording unto them means, through the improvement whereof, they were brought thereunto, and might be furniſhed with power and ſtrength to perſevere therin, againſt all the malice of their adverſaries.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The fourth text is the 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25. the words are theſe, <hi>(viz.)</hi> In meekneſſe inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe themſelves: if God peradventure will give them repentance to the acknowledging of the truth; from whence it is conceived, that repentance is not to be obtained by the uſe of externall means, but is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto men, or wrought in them by the immediate hand of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I anſwer, That this inference doth neither ſuite with that which is expreſt in the 18, and 21, verſes, afore-going in the chapter: nor yet with the text it ſelf.</p>
               <p>For firſt, in the 18, verſ. it is declared, that ſome by the errour of <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus</hi> (who taught, that the reſurrection was paſt already) had their faith over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, that is to ſay, were thereby ſeduced to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of that opinion; and from the deniall of that, the foundation of God and godlineſſe to Apoſtates, from all the duties of Chriſtianity, and workes of repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, implyed verſe 19, which muſt needs be imputed either to ſome change and alteration in God, or elſe in themſelves: but unto God it cannot be imputed, for he changeth not, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6. His foundation ſtandeth ſure; therefore it muſt be imputed to themſelves: and if ſo, then it muſt therupon needs follow, That repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in men is not any otherwiſe obtained, then through their own improvement of the means vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed for that end; for if that it did not wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119970:47"/>
upon themſelves, then it ſhould be altogether impoſſible, either that any thing done or miſ-done, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted or committed, ſhould be prejudiciall unto them in that reſpect.</p>
               <p>And that this is ſo, doth further appear by that in the 21, verſe, the words whereof are as followeth: If a man therefore PURGE HIMSELF from theſe, he ſhall be a veſſell of honour, ſanctified and meet for his Maſters uſe, &amp;c. Wherein is plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared how, and by what means Sanctification (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in repentance conſiſteth) is to be endeavoured and obtained, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That every man by the Doctrine of the Reſurrection and Glory in the World to come, through conformity to Chriſt, verſe 11, 12. DOE PURGE HIMSELF from the foreſaid opinions, with all the evil conſequences thereof. Flee youthfull luſts, and follow after righteouſneſſe, faith, charity, peace, with thoſe that call on the Lord out of a pure heart; the neglect whereof occaſioned the falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of thoſe afore-mentioned, as by the coherence of theſe verſes doth manifeſtly appear.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor doth it any better ſuite with the Text it ſelf: wherein <hi>Timothy</hi> is required with meekneſſe to inſtruct thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, the end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as alſo of Gods forbearance, being every where in the Scriptures declared to be none other than mens repentance; and therefore to whomſoever the ſame is vouchſafed, the poſſibility of their repentance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by muſt needs be ſuppoſed; becauſe it doth not ſtand with the wiſdome of God to propound an end, from ſuch means whereby it cannot poſſibly be effected. And its frequently to be obſerved in Chriſt, that he directeth his inſtruction only to thoſe that have ears
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119970:47"/>
to hear, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.15, 13, 43. <hi>Reve.</hi> 2.7, 11, 17, 29, verſes, chapter 3, 6, 13, 22, verſes, Thereby doubtleſſe to informe us, that if men were abſolutely uncapable of hearing and receiving the ſame, it ſhould not at all be preached unto them.</p>
               <p>Beſides, It cannot be ſuppoſed, that God ſhould command his ſervants, to caſt holy things unto Swine to be trampled under their feet, or to ſpil the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and incorruptible Seed of his Word, as water upon the ground, (the conſequence of the contrary opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) ſeeing that it is delivered by him for a generall rule to be obſerved by them; That when men by their preaching unto them were fully enlightened in the knowledge of his Grace, and of eternall Salvation brought unto them by Jeſus Chriſt, and ſhould then wilfully and ſtubbornly reiect the ſame, put it from them, and judge themſelves unworthy thereof, (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by declaring that no hopes of their repentance were to be expected from thence) that then they ſhould depart from them, and ceaſe to preach any further un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.45, 46, 47.</p>
               <p>And therefore it may not be imagined, that either the perſons intended in the text, whom <hi>Timothy</hi> was required to inſtruct, or any other to whom the Goſpel was ſent to be preached, were altogether uncapable of improving the ſame, to the end thereof.</p>
               <p>Which conſidered, the meaning of the Apoſtle in this place, muſt be underſtood only as if he ſhould have commanded <hi>Timothy</hi> to inſtruct with meekneſſe, thoſe that oppoſe themſelves, becauſe that paradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture at one time or other they might hearken therun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, lay it to heart, and improve the ſame to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:119970:48"/>God being ſaid (as was ſhewed before) not only to give unto us ſuch things wherewith we are immediatly poſſeſſed by his meer devotion, but all ſuch things likewiſe which are obtained by our laborious induſtry, and improvement of the means vouchſafed unto us for thoſe ends: He giveth unto us richly all things to enjoy, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17. Day by Day, he giveth unto us our daily bread.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The fifth text alleadged, is <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.5, 6. The words are theſe, Even ſo at this preſent time alſo there is a remnant according to the Election of Grace, and if by Grace, then is it no more of workes, otherwiſe Grace is no more Grace: but if it be of workes, then it is no more of Grace, otherwiſe worke is no more worke. From whence it is conceived that by the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, all workes on mens part, either in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to their Election or Salvation, are wholly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded; and that there is not any thing required to be done by them thereunto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To which I anſwer: firſt, That it was ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before in anſwer to <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28, 29, 30. That Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is not in the firſt, but in the ſecond <hi>Adam;</hi> not of the diſobedient but of the repentant, godly, rich in Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which with comparing the 4, verſe with the 5, before alleadged, will receive further confirmation; For when in the 4, verſ. the Apoſtle having declared, That thoſe whom God reſerved to himſelf in the daies of <hi>Elias,</hi> were ſuch only who in obedience unto him, refuſed to bow the knee to the Image of <hi>Baal.</hi> In the 5, verſe he addeth, That even ſo at this preſent time alſo, there is a remnant according to the Election of Grace; which is as if he ſhould have ſaid, Whereas a great number of the Iſraelites are rejected and caſt off
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119970:48"/>
from the favour of God, you are not to conceive them to be ſo rejected for any other cauſe, then for their wilfull and ſtubborn diſobedience againſt his word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed unto them, chap. 1.17. chap. 10.18, 21. chap. 11.20. For as in the daies of <hi>Elias</hi> he reſerved to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, all thoſe that hearkened unto him, and refuſed to bow to the Image of <hi>Baal:</hi> Even ſo likewiſe at this time he reſerveth to himſelf for his ſonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, all thoſe that ſubmit themſelves to his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, chap. 10.3. Harden not their hearts, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3.8, 17, 18, 19. Nor judge themſelves unworthy of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46, 47. Nor yet doth he ſo reject any of them for their unbelief; but that he will readily accept of them again, if that they doe not continue therein, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.23.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I anſwer, That when the Apoſtle ſaith, That E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection to Salvation is not of workes, but of Grace, he doth not thereby exclude all works in reference ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, but the workes of perfection, according to the law of innocency and creation; only from which eſtate man-kinde being fallen, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.29. their Juſtification and Salvation thereby muſt needs be altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible.</p>
               <p>That Grace doth not exclude all Workes, doth evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appear from hence, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That integrity and uprightnes of heart (which properly conſiſteth in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and chearfull conformity to all the Commandments of God made known unto us, ſo far forth as opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ability doth afford) is required of every man to his Salvation, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1, 2, 7. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.48. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.16, 17, 21.</p>
               <p>In which reſpect Chriſt implieth the young man, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.21, 23. (that refuſed to ſell all that he had
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119970:49"/>
and give to the poor, and to take up his Croſſe and follow him, when it was required of him, to be imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and incapable of entring into eternall life. And S. <hi>John</hi> denieth that man to have the love of God dwelling in him, that ſeeth his brother ſtand in need, and ſhutteth up his bowels of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion towards him, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.17. And from hence it is, that S. <hi>James</hi> declareth, That that faith which obtaineth juſtification is made perfect tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough workes, <hi>Iames</hi> 2.21, 22, 23<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Abrahams</hi> integrity engaged him to offer up his Son upon the Altar, when it was required of him; and by offering of him up, he is ſaid to fulfill the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which ſaid that he belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, God, <hi>Jam. 2.23.</hi> Which plainly argueth that all knowne duties, or works within a mans power to be performed, are ſo eſſentiall to integrity and faith, that they cannot poſſibly be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed: whence <hi>Abraham,</hi> that one while is ſaid to be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by faith, <hi>Rom. 4.9.</hi> is otherwhiles by S. <hi>James</hi> chap. <hi>2.21.</hi> declared to be juſtified by workes.</note>. For where workes (ſuch as are within a mans power) are wanting, integrity is wanting; and where integrity is wanting, faith is dead, verſe 17, 26. Unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.6. And not to be diſtinguiſhed from that of the Devil, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.19.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing then that all ſuch workes which are within mens power to performe, are required of them to their Salvation: It muſt needs be granted, when the Apoſtle ſaith, That it is not of workes, that his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therin is none other, then that it is not of workes of perfection according to the law of our creation, which are impoſſible for any man to performe, ſo as to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119970:49"/>
be juſtified thereby, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16. And that the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence betwixt Workes, and Grace, or the Law, and the Goſpel, ſtandeth only in this, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That the firſt requireth unto life, that which is impoſſible unto men in their fallen eſtate: the later no more then what is poſſible unto them therein; and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that life and Salvation which could not be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by any through the covenant of workes, may be obtained by all, through the covenant of Grace: which will more evidently appear, if it be conſidered.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That the only and ſpeciall reaſon, why the firſt Covenant was repealed, and the ſecond vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed, is declared to be this, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That the firſt could not give life unto men, (that is to ſay, in their fallen eſtate, for in the eſtate of innocency, it muſt needs be acknowledged it could) If there had been a Law that could have given life (ſaith the text, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.21.) veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly righteouſneſſe had been by the Law, but in regard it could not, therefore (as the words of the Apoſtle in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8.6, 7. doe plainly intimate) the Lord found fault therewith, aboliſhed it, and gave unto men a more excellent Covenant inſtead thereof, (that is to ſay, a covenant wherby ſalvation might be obtained by them in their fallen eſtate) for, ſeeing that the goodneſſe of God, and his deſire of mens Salvation was ſuch, as cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to aboliſh the firſt Covenant, becauſe it could not give life unto them: no reaſonable man can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that his ſaid goodneſſe and love towards them would ſuffer him to give unto them a ſecond Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, as faulty and unable, to give life unto them, as that aboliſhed: and if not, Then foraſmuch as by the later workes are required to be performed by men to their Salvation, as well as by the former; the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119970:50"/>
of the later above the former, muſt needs be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to conſiſt only in this, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That the workes required thereby, and the conditions upon which life is promiſed therin, are performable by men in their fallen eſtate, whereas thoſe required thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by the other were not. In which reſpect it is, that in the 6, verſe, the Apoſtle declareth, that the later is eſtabliſhed upon better promiſes, then the form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That thoſe that endeavoured to reduce men from the Doctrine of the Goſpel, to the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law, are by the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10. char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with tempting God, by putting a yoak upon the necks of the Diſciples, which they were not able to bear. And to the Galathians which were perverted by thoſe falſe teachers, <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1, 3. thus writeth: O fooliſh Galathians, who hath bewitched you, that ye ſhould not obey the truth? Are ye ſo fooliſh that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving begun in the Spirit, are ye made perfect by the Law? which plainly argueth, that the Doctrine of the Goſpel which they preached was no ſuch yoak, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that then they themſelves in preaching the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, &amp; turning men from <hi>Moſes</hi> to Chriſt, ſhould have bin liable to the ſame reproof which they laid upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: And as fooliſh ſhould the Galathians have been, in hearkening to them preaching the Goſpel: as they were in hearkening to the falſe Apoſtles preaching the Law. For of two yoaks alike intollerable, wiſdome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth a man to chooſe the one as ſoon as the other, and not to prefer the one before the other; and there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore unleſſe that we will ſuppoſe the Apoſtles to be guilty of tempting God in the ſame nature, wherein they accuſe and cenſure others, (and thereby to make
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119970:50"/>
themſelves inexcuſable, both before God and men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1.) we muſt needs conclude that the yoak or precepts of the Goſpel, which they endeavoured to impoſe upon men, were not intollerable or grievous, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.3. Like unto thoſe of the Law, but eaſie and light, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.30. and ſo conſequently, that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, life and ſalvation impoſſible by the former, is poſſible, and may be attained by the later.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That <hi>Paul</hi> in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7, 9. ſpeaking of the Law, calleth it the Miniſtration of death and of condemnation. And contrariwiſe ſpeaking of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, or New Teſtament, he calleth it the miniſtration of righteouſneſſe, and in verſe the 6, ſaith, That the firſt killeth, but the later giveth life: Now foraſmuch as the Law in it's own nature, is neither the miniſtration of death nor condemnation, being holy, juſt and good, promiſing life, and would aſſuredly bring us to the poſſeſſion thereof, could we but obſerve what it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, or attain unto that originall innocency and puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in which we were created; therefore it is ſo called only, in reſpect that in the neceſſary conſequence ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (by reaſon of our inability to fulfill the ſame) it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth ſuch unto us. And therefore if that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the new Covenant were no more perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able then thoſe of the Law: the Goſpel could not be called, the miniſtration of righteouſneſſe and life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more then the Law: becauſe it is the ſavour of death unto death, unto all thoſe that diſobey it as well as the Law, <hi>John</hi> 3.19. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.28, 29. and conferreth neither righteouſnes nor life unto any that obſerve it not, any more then the Law; therefore whereas it is called, the miniſtration of righteouſneſſe and life, in oppoſition to the Law; it muſt needs be
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119970:51"/>
underſtood in this reſpect, That righteouſneſſe, life and Salvation, impoſſible by the Law, may be obtained by it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The ſame Apoſtle likewiſe diſcourſing of the two Covenants, in the ninth and tenth chapters of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and having in the 32, verſe of the 9. chapter, after a large diſcourſe concerning the ſame, concluded righteouſneſſe not to be attainable by the Law: in the 8, verſe of the 10. chapter, he declareth, That the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe that is by the Goſpel, is nigh unto us (even in our mouthes and in our hearts) then which nothing can be more near unto us. And in <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.11, 12, 13, 14. whereunto he hath alluſion, to prevent all objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning this thing, <hi>Moſes</hi> thus ſpeaketh: The commandment that I command thee this day, it is not hidden from thee, neither is it farre off: It is not in Heaven that thou ſhouldſt ſay, who ſhall go up for us to Heaven, and bring it unto us, that we may hear it and do it. Neither is it beyond the Sea, that thou ſhouldſt ſay, who ſhall goe over the Sea for us and bring it unto us, that we may hear it and doe it? But the word is nigh unto thee, in thy mouth and in thy heart, that thou maieſt doe it; then which, what words can poſſibly be uſed more emphatically to ſet forth to our underſtandings that righteouſneſſe which was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible by the Law, is not only poſſible, but eaſie to be obtained by the Goſpel; it is not hidden from us, nor far off, but near unto us, in our mouthes, and in our hearts, that we may doe it. Far from their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that affirme, That God muſt bow the Heavens and come down into our Souls, and infuſe into them ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall light and faith, before that we can either underſtand or doe any thing requiſite to our Salvation.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:119970:51"/>5. But to put this point out of all diſpute. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Scriptures do informe us, that according to the Law of workes, There is none righteous; none that doth good, no, not one, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.10, 12. and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding doe alſo informe us, That <hi>Abel, Heb.</hi> 11.4. <hi>Noah, Gen.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Abimelech, Gen.</hi> 20.4. <hi>Lot.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2, 8. &amp; <hi>Zechariah, Luke</hi> 1.6. were all of them righteous men. That <hi>Jacob Mat.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Simeon, Luke</hi> 2.25. <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius,</hi> were juſt men, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.1, 22. That <hi>Job,</hi> chap. 1.18. <hi>Aſa,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.17. and others, were upright and perfect men, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15. That <hi>Ahimaas</hi> the ſon of <hi>Zadock,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.27. and <hi>Barnabas</hi> the ſon of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, were both of them good men, <hi>Acts</hi> 11.24. It muſt therefore neceſſarily follow, That what was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible by the Law or covenant of workes, is poſſible by the Goſpel, or covenant of Grace: and that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, juſtice, goodneſs, and eternall Salvation, which could not be obtained by the former, hath, and may be obtained by the later.</p>
               <p>And yet notwithſtanding, although that the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace (or the Goſpel) doth require to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the performance of all ſuch good workes, which are within our power to performe; yet ought it, and that eminently to be eſteemed by us a Covenant of Grace: and that for theſe reſpects.</p>
               <p>Firſt, In regard of the time, (ſtate, and condition, wherein all man-kinde were) when this Covenant was vouchſafed unto them. That is to ſay, When all man-kinde by reaſon of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion, were brought under the guilt of condemnation, and everlaſting ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion, having no eie to pity them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.5, 6. nor ability to deliver themſelves from peace (but muſt of neceſſity have periſhed therein for ever,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119970:52"/>
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.16, 17, 18.) That then God the Father of all pity and compaſſion, commended his love unto them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8. and forth of his infinite goodneſſe, was graciouſly pleaſed by the death of his only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son, to pay the price of their redemption, to ranſome them from that eſtate, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.21, 22. and to ſay unto them, return from corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ye periſhing ſons of men, and live, and in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereunto, to grant this Covenant of life and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That becauſe in this Covenant God requireth of us leſſe than his due, and no more then what in our fallen eſtate we are ſufficiently enabled to performe and render unto him; we owed unto him perfect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, being in creation made perfect by him, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.29. he asketh of us but integrity conſiſtent with nocency and imperfection ſo conſidered) as plainly appeareth by that which is ſpoken concerning <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 9.4. <hi>Aſa,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 15.14. <hi>Simeon, Luke</hi> 2.25. <hi>Cornelius, Acts</hi> 10.22. and divers others, declared to be perfect, juſt, and upright men, (notwithſtanding all their frailties, ſenſurable by the covenant of works) and are by God approved and accepted, in reference to his covenant of Grace.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In regard that although we have our lives of Grace, and that he asketh of us ſo little in compariſon of what we are indebted unto him, he is ſo bountiful, as to grant us a reward of all our workes, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.6. ye ſuch an exceeding great reward, that our light af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions which are but for a moment, worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternall weight of Glory, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.17.</p>
               <p>That he ſhould grant us any reward at all for any
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119970:52"/>
ſervice done unto him, (if we conſider that it was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his owne which we gave unto him, that we received it of him, and that we our ſelves likewiſe are his, and that by a double debt) it muſt needs accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the humble confeſſion of <hi>David,</hi> be acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged great bounty in him, 1 <hi>Chro.</hi> 29.13, 14, 15, 16. but that he ſhould ſo far regard our bounden affection, as to reward us for our very meaneſt workes, even for a cup of cold water given in his name; and to grant us ſo great a reward for ſo ſmall a worke: as a Prophets reward (doubtles one of the greateſt) for but receiving a Prophet in the name of a Prophet, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.41. muſt needs be acknowledged tranſcendent Grace, love that paſſeth all knowledge.</p>
               <p>The 6. Text is <hi>Jerem.</hi> 31.31, 32, 33, 34. the words whereof are as followeth: Behold the daies come, ſaith the Lord, that I will make a new covenant with the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and with the houſe of <hi>Judah:</hi> Not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the covenant that I made with their fathers in the day that I tooke them by the hand, to bring them out of the Land of <hi>Egypt;</hi> which covenant they brake, although that I was a husband unto them. But this ſhall be the covenant that I will make with the houſe of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> After thoſe daies ſaith the Lord, I wil put my Law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From whence it is ordinarily objected, That God hath covenanted neceſſarily and unavoidably to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct ſome men in the knowledge of himſelf, and by putting his Lawes into their hearts, to worke in them repentance, faith, &amp;c. The which objection, as it ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth ſome men to be more accepted and beloved of God, in the eſtate of unbelief then others; hath been
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119970:53"/>
often before diſproved; yet in regard that it hath ſo ſeeming a countenance of truth put upon it by this Scripture, with ſome others ſpeaking in the ſame language, I ſhall further anſwer thereunto, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring,</p>
               <p>Firſt, That it may be conſidered, that ſeeing there are but two Covenants known at any time to be given by God unto men, the one of works, the other of Grace: all man-kinde muſt be concluded, either to be under the firſt, or under the later of them.</p>
               <p n="1">1. But under the firſt they are not, becauſe that God finding fault therewith hath repealed it, cauſed it to wax old, and to vaniſh away, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.7-13.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, Hath redeemed all men from the curſe and penalty thereof, death, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Hath prohibited all men from ſeeking righteouſneſſe thereby, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10. <hi>Romans</hi> 10.3. And therefore all men muſt be concluded to be under the ſecond. And not for theſe reaſons only; But alſo,</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, Becauſe that the duties of the ſecond Covenant <hi>(viz.)</hi> Repentance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is required of all, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.30. And</p>
               <p n="5">5. Fifthly, That Salvation the end thereof is thereupon promiſed unto all, whence thoſe that periſh are charged with neglecting Salvation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And laſtly, Becauſe that the ſecond death, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.11. or condemnation inflicted by Chriſt at the laſt day, is none other then the penalty of the breach of the ſecond Covenant. This is the condemnation of the world (ſaith <hi>S. John</hi>) Chap. 3.19. That light is
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119970:53"/>
come into the world, and men love darkneſſe rather then light, becauſe their deeds are evil: Which later reaſon receiveth confirmation from hence, That Chriſt by a moſt lively embleme in the Parable of the Talents, hath declared unto us, That God at that day will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire no more of any man, but according to the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents of Grace delivered unto them by himſelf, the Mediatour of the new Covenant, and will then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn none, but for not well uſing what they had, ſo received of him, whereupon it doth neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, That all men being under the new Covenant, whatſoever Grace neceſſary to Salvation, is therein by God promiſed unto any (he being faithfull that hath promiſed, and the Covenant confirmed unto all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde by the bloud of Jeſus Chriſt) the ſame muſt needs be acknowledged to be granted unto all. And then foraſmuch as we ſee, that all men have not the Law and Fear of God written in them (otherwiſe then was ſhewed before concerning the Gentiles, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14, 15.) nor their ſtony hearts taken out of their fleſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> we muſt not therefore imagine, that God hath covenanted abſolutely to do theſe things for any men.</p>
               <p>But there are two things in this Text, which tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row want of due conſideration miſ-lead many men from the right underſtanding thereof.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe it is ſaid, That this Covenant which God promiſeth to make with the Iews in the laſt daies, ſhould not be like unto the Covenant that he made with their fathers, when he brought them out of the Land of <hi>Aegypt</hi> (the which Covenant they brake, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) From whence it is conceived, That as the firſt Covenant could not by any be kept, ſo the later cannot by any
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:119970:54"/>
that are comprehended therein be broken.</p>
               <p>For the clearing of this miſtake, I deſire that it may be obſerved,</p>
               <p>That if by theſe two Covenants here ſpoken of, we muſt underſtand the Law and the Goſpel, Works and Grace (which is much queſtioned by ſome, who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them to be particular Covenants, proper and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to the Iews only, and ſo nothing at all to the point in hand) that they were neither of them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made, untill the time that God brought the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> out of the Land of <hi>Aegypt.</hi> And therefore much leſſe, until the daies of the Prophet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> as this Text ſeemeth to import.</p>
               <p>That the firſt Covenant was given unto our firſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in Paradiſe, appeareth from hence, That the curſe thereof entered into the world by <hi>Adam,</hi> and raigned over all men before the Law was given at mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> Rom. 5.14. For where the curſe of the Law is inflicted, there the breach of the Law muſt needs be imputed. And ſeeing (as the Apoſtle teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.13. that ſin is not imputed, where there is no Law given, therefore the Law muſt needs be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be given unto <hi>Adam,</hi> and in him to all man-kinde, before the puniſhment thereof, death, thorow his diſobedience did enter into the world, and raign therein. And like as the Law was given unto <hi>Adam,</hi> before he incurred the puniſhment thereof. So the Goſpel or ſecond Covenant muſt needs be granted immediately to ſucceed upon his tranſgreſſion of the firſt: becauſe that otherwiſe the curſe of the Law, ſhould forthwith, according as it was threatned, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17.) have ſeized upon him to have deſtroied him, and in him all man-kinde then in his loins ſinning in
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119970:54"/>
him, the truth whereof is confirmed unto us from hence.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the end of Gods patience and forbearance towards ſinners, is none other then their Repentance and Salvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4. Deſpiſeſt thou (ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaking to the Gentiles) the riches of his goodneſſe, and forbearance, and long-ſuffering, not knowing that the goodneſſe of God leadeth thee to Repentance. Again, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. <hi>Peter</hi> telleth thoſe that ſcoffed at Gods forbearance towards them in their wickedneſſe (contrary as they ſuppoſed to his threats denounced againſt them) That God was not ſlack con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Promiſe, as they counted ſlackneſſe, but long-ſuffering, not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repentance. And <hi>Paul,</hi> in <hi>Act.</hi> 17.26, 27. plainly informeth us, That the end why God made of one bloud (that is to ſay of <hi>Adam</hi>) all Nations of men to dwell upon the face of the earth, was, That they ſhould ſeek the Lord: Now foraſmuch as ſeeking of the Lord, Repentance and the obtaining of Salvation doth neceſſarily preſuppoſe the granting and exhibiting of the new Covenant: theſe ends be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing otherwiſe impoſſible to be attained, it muſt needs follow, That as God is declared to ſpare and forbear <hi>Adam,</hi> and all men, to the end they might repent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that in reference to theſe ends he vouchſafed unto them the Covenant of his Grace, whereby they might be enabled to attain thereunto.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Beſides, If that God ſhould have ſpared our firſt parents, and granted unto them the procreation of ſeed, and not in order to the Grace of the new Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Redemption from death, the curſe of the Law, and Salvation in the world to come, thorow Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119970:55"/>
then there ſhould have been no proportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the ſinne of man-kinde in <hi>Adam,</hi> and the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment thereof, becauſe ſinning but <hi>in potentia,</hi> they ſhould be puniſhed <hi>in actu,</hi> which inequality of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding is by God in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. diſclaimed; ſo that if he had not prepared for man-kinde another life after death, and vouchſafed means to make them happy therein, they ſhould never perſonally have ſuffered death, but ſuch as was their ſin; ſuch ſhould have been their puniſhment.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Moreover, If that the Covenant of Grace had not been from the beginning, then Salvation ſhould not have been from the beginning, ſeeing that it is of Grace only, and not of works, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8. Whereas therefore the Scriptures enformeth us, That remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſins, acceptation with God, and conſequently Salvation was preached unto <hi>Cain,</hi> Gen. 4.6, 7. And that <hi>Abel,</hi> the third man on earth, obtained the ſame, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4. it muſt needs be granted, That the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace was vouchſafed unto men from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, even from the very time that they ſtood in any need thereof.</p>
               <p>Theſe two Covenants of Works and Grace then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made and given ſo long before the time, implied by the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> his words, cannot poſſibly be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood to import the time wherein either the firſt was, or the later ſhould be made with man-kinde, but the time wherein the firſt was, and the later ſhould be more clearly made known and demonſtrated both un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Iews and unto others, then at any time from the beginning of the world they had been. In which reſpect it is that Chriſt (ſpeaking unto his Diſciples) ſaith, Bleſſed are your eyes, for they ſee, and your
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119970:55"/>
ears, for they hear; for verily I ſay unto you, That many Prophets and righteous men, have deſired to ſee theſe things which ye ſee, and have not ſeen them, and to hear theſe things which you hear, and have not heard them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.16, 17. And hence are the words of the Apoſtle, in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10, 11, Unto me who am leſſe then the leaſt of all Saints, is this Grace given, that I ſhould preach amongſt the Gentiles, the unſearchable riches of Chriſt, and to make all men ſee, what is the fellowſhip of the myſtery which from the beginning of the world hath been hid in God, who created all things by Jeſus Chriſt, to the intent that now unto the principalities and powers in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly places, might be known by the Church the manifold wiſdome of God, according to the eternall purpoſe which he purpoſed in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord. And hereunto alſo is the words of the ſame Apoſtle, in <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.25, 26. to be applied.</p>
               <p>Which conſidered, the emphaſis contained in the words of the Prophets (before rehearſed) are to be underſtood only, as if the Lord ſhould have ſaid, I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited unto your fathers the Covenant of works, when he brought them out of the Land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> not to the intent that they ſhould ſeek righteouſneſſe and life by it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.7-18, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3. but to ſhew them their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity and weakneſſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.22. And that they ſhould ſeek Salvation only thorow the promiſe preached unto <hi>Abraham</hi> their father four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years before the Law was given, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.17. The which Covenant they brake, though that I was a huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band unto them. But the Covenant of my Grace preached unto you by all the Prophets ſince the world began, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.70. <hi>Act.</hi> 43.26.22, 23. and which in
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119970:56"/>
the later daies I will more clearly demonſtrate unto your children by the Miniſtery of my Son, is not like unto that Covenant, being eſtabliſhed upon better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, wherby I ſhall ſo abundantly commend my love unto them. That although poſſibly they may deſpiſe the ſame, and turn my Grace therein manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted unto them into wantonneſſe, yet ſurely (or in all reaſon) they will not, but will reverence my Sonne, when they ſee him, receive my word from him into their hearts, and become obedient unto me.</p>
               <p>For God having made men rationall (in reference whereunto only he treateth with them, by arguments different from all other his creatures) and naturally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed to their own happineſſe, whenſoever more clearly then ordinary, he openeth unto them a way thereunto, and uſeth Arguments extraordinary to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dear them unto him for his goodneſſe towards them therein (in the Scriptures) he often taketh it for granted, That then more eſpecially they will be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the love and perpetual Obedience of him, as is ſhewed in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.7, 8, 9. where from the conſideration of the goodneſſe that he had vouchſafed to the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the mercies and multitude of loving kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes that he had beſtowed upon them, in ſaving them by the Angel of his preſence, redeeming them in his love and pity, carrying them thorow the wilderneſſe, and in all their afflictions being afflicted with them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he concludeth them to be his people, in ſuch ſort that they would never deal untruly with him, becauſe that (although poſſibly they might, as in verſ. 10. it, appeareth they were, yet) rationally they could not be unthankfull unto him, nor diſobedient againſt him
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119970:56"/>
after ſuch extraordinary mercies received from him. From whence alſo it is that <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſtileth thoſe men that refuſed and oppoſed the Goſpel of Salvation, when it was preached unto them unreaſonable men, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.2. degenerated from men into brute beaſts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.32. becauſe that reaſon cannot oppoſe it ſelf. And therefore ſeeing that it teacheth and directeth all men endued therewith, to ſeek their own happineſſe and felicity, as it muſt needs prohibit them the rejection thereof, and the abuſe of the means leading thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: So on the contrary, it muſt needs engage them to ſincerity of love, and hearty affection towards God, by how much the more he diſcovereth himſelf in Love, Mercy and Goodneſſe towards them in that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>And hereupon it is, that God conſidering how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly the riches of his grace, Fatherly affection, and bowels of compaſſion towards all men, ſhould by the Miniſtery of Ieſus Chriſt at his appearance be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, and by ſigns and wonders, confirmed beyond all contradiction (to the Iews eſpecially, to whom moſt immediately he was ſent, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.24.) more than at any time from the beginning of the world it had been (inſomuch that hearing and behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame, and not rejecting reaſon and humanity, and judging themſelves unworthy of everlaſting life, they could not poſſibly but rejoyce therein, be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for their former diſobedience againſt ſo merciful a God, receive with thankfulnes his holy inſtructions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered unto them, and ever afterwards become obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent unto him, he concludeth therefore that they would be converted, and united unto him for ever; although that through ſavage and brutiſh folly (unto which
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119970:57"/>
men may poſſibly degenerate, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 46.6, 7, 8.) they both might, and did reject, and deſpiſe his unſpeaka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble goodneſſe towards them. All which is moſt clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plainly demonſtrated by the words of Chriſt himſelf, in <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. from the 33. to the 39. <hi>Mark</hi> 10. from the firſt to the ninth. And <hi>Luke</hi> 20. from the 9. to the 15.</p>
               <p>Hear a Parable (ſaith Chriſt ſpeaking to the Iews, to whom the promiſe in <hi>Ier.</hi> 31. hath the moſt eſpecial relation) There was a certain houſholder which plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Vineyard, and hedged it round about, and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged a wine-preſſe in it, and built a tower, and let it out to huſbandmen, and went into a farre countrey; and when the time of fruit drew near, he ſent his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, that he might receive from the huſbandmen the fruit of the vineyard, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the huſbandman took his ſervants, and beat one, and killed another, and ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned another. Again he ſent other ſervants more then the firſt, and they did unto them likewiſe, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 38.15, 16. <hi>Acts</hi> 7.51, 52. <hi>Luke</hi> 9.49, 50.</p>
               <p>Whereupon (to the end, that he might to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of all men and Angels, expreſſe his patience, goodneſſe, and hearty affection to the Salvation of the very worſt of men) the Lord of the Vineyard (ſaith <hi>Luke</hi>) ſaid unto himſelf, What ſhall I doe? I will ſend my beloved Sonne, my only and well-beloved Sonne (<hi>Mark</hi> 12.6.) ſaying, THEY WILL, (note) Reverence my Sonne, when they ſee him, <hi>Mar.</hi> 12.6. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.37. (But what followeth?) when the huſbandmen ſaw his Son, they reaſoned among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſaying, This is the heir, come let us kill him, that the inheritance may be ours: and they caſt him out
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119970:57"/>
of the vineyard, and killed him.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The miſtake concerning the ſence of this Scripture, is grounded upon theſe words <hi>(viz.)</hi> I will put my laws into their mindes, and write them in their hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> From whence it is conceived, that God hath promiſed unavoidably, to beget the Love, Fear, and Obedience of himſelf, in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons, not in others.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the clearing whereof, it is to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, that the reaſon why God promiſed to write his laws in the hearts of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the later daies, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then in the former, was, becauſe that in the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter daies (by the Miniſtery of his Sonne) he would more abundantly demonſtrate his love and goodneſſe unto them, then formerly he had done by the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of any of his ſervants; The which although it did moſt powerfully tend to imprint his Love and Fear in them, and to perſwade them to deny all ungodlines and worldly luſts, and to ſerve him in righteouſnes and true holines all their daies, <hi>Lu.</hi> 1.74, 75. yet foraſmuch as that means did not inevitably effect the ſame in them, for if it had, then they ſhould all of them been converted thereby: therefore it cannot from hence be rightly inferred from this text, That God hath promiſed ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to beget the love and fear of himſelf in any one man more then another.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is alſo to be conſidered, That when God (in the Scriptures) ſaith, that he will doe this or that, it doth not alwaies imply, an abſolute and peremptory reſolution in him, neceſſarily to enforce and bring the ſame to paſſe, but to adminiſter ſuch means, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he knoweth, that men either by a direct or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct uſe thereof, will, or may be induced
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119970:58"/>
to the doing of that which he ſaith, he will doe.</p>
               <p>In the later reſpect it is that he ſpeaketh, when he ſaith, I will harden <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart: becauſe that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering him to be a proud, covetous tyrant, he knew that he would take occaſion of obſtinacy againſt him by reaſon of his mercy towards the oppreſſed <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> (notwithſtanding all his ſignes and wonders ſhewed unto him, powerfully tending to humble him to the very earth before him) and refuſe to let them depart out of his Land, as he was commanded.</p>
               <p>And in the former reſpect, are the words of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 2.4. to be underſtood; when he ſaith, That God would have all men to be ſaved. And ſo likewiſe are the words of Chriſt, in <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.32. to be taken, where he ſaith, And I, if I were lifted up from the earth, I WILL DRAW all men after me; becauſe that by his Death and Reſurrection he ſhould further manifeſt himſelf to all men to be the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of the world: For as when he affordeth unto men the means of repentance, he is ſaid thereby to purge them from their filthineſſe, though that they be not actually purged thereby (as was ſhewed before in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24.13.) So (according to theſe Scriptures) when he diſpenſeth meanes extraordinary, tending to lead men to Converſion and Salvation, Then more eſpecially it is ſaid, That he will put his Laws into their hearts, will draw them to Chriſt, and will have them to be ſaved.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It is to be conſidered, That like as God faith, That he will write his Laws in mens hearts, cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe their hearts, make them new hearts and new ſpirits, <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.33. <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.16. <hi>Ier.</hi> 36.26. Even ſo
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119970:58"/>
he alſo requireth men to write his Laws in their hearts, <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.3. Circumciſe their hearts, <hi>Ier.</hi> 4.4. and make to themſelves new hearts and new ſpirits, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 19.31. Now as the Evangelical precepts are not to be expounded againſt the promiſes, ſo neither are the promiſes thereof to be expounded againſt the precepts; and if conſidered together, they are to be underſtood, as if God ſhould ſay, I will afford means unto you for theſe ends, do you improve them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
               <p>If it be ſaid, that theſe precepts ſerve only to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe unto men, that which God promiſeth to work in them.</p>
               <p>It is anſwered firſt, That this is a very forraign ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and will neither be warranted by Scripture or ſound reaſon: God being never known to require of men that which he himſelf promiſeth to doe for them, and moſt irrationall to conceive, that he ſhould not rather expreſſe his goodneſſe towards men, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring them to wait upon him for the things that he purpoſeth to beſtow upon them, then to give them precepts for the doing thereof, thereby to divert their hopes and expectation, as from the promiſes, and to ſet them on work to beat the air, or to make brick without ſtraw.</p>
               <p>But ſecondly, ſeeing it is manifeſt, that theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts are unto all men, and as manifeſt that all men have not the things enjoyned therein effected in them, it cannot in any wiſe be ſuppoſed, that the intent of God in them ſhould be to expreſſe what he himſelf would work in men, but to enforme us that his promiſes to put his Laws in mens mindes to write them in their hearts, to make them new hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:119970:59"/>
conſiſteth only in affording unto them means ſerving for thoſe ends, which they themſelves are enjoyned to improve for the effecting thereof.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Laſtly, It is to be obſerved, That thoſe very perſons the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to whom this promiſe hath the moſt principal relation, unto whom the Apoſtle moſt directly applieth the ſame, in the 10 Chapter to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews,</hi> are notwithſtanding by him evidently decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be under a poſſibility of ſinning wilfully againſt the knowledge of the truth, of trampling the Sonne of God under their feet, and counting his bloud the bloud of this Covenant wherewith they were ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an unholy thing, and of doing deſpite unto the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Grace, and thereby of incurring to themſelves the ſoreſt puniſhment, judgement and fiery indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which poſſibly could not be, if that God in this Covenant had abſolutely promiſed, or underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to put his laws in their hearts, and write them in their mindes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as it is ſuppoſed, or any otherwiſe then by adminiſtring unto them means for thoſe ends, which poſſibly might be neglected and contemned by them. But becauſe that this Scripture ſerveth ſo clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſcover the intent and nature of this Covenant, it ſhall be rehearſed <hi>verbatim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heb. 10.16. <hi>This is the Covenant that I will make with them after thoſe daies, ſaith the Lord: I will put my laws into their hearts, and in their mindes will I write them: And their ſinnes and iniquities will I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member no more. Now where remiſſion of theſe is, there is no more offering for ſin. Having therefore, brethren, boldneſſe</hi> or liberty, <hi>to enter into the holieſt by the bloud of Jeſus, By a new and living way which he hath conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated for us, through the vail, that is to ſay, his fleſh:
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119970:59"/>
And having an high Prieſt over the houſe of God: Let us draw near with a true heart, in full aſſurance of faith, having our hearts ſprinkled from an evil conſcience, and our bodies waſhed with pure water. And let us conſider one another, to provoke unto love; and to good workes: Not forſaking the aſſembling of our ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is: but exhorting one another, and ſo much the more as ye ſee the day approaching. For if we ſinne wilfully after that we have received the knowledge of the truth, there remaineth no more ſacrifice for ſinnes, But a certain fearfull looking for of judgement, and fiery indignation, which ſhall devour the adverſaries. He that deſpiſed Moſes Law, died without mercy under two or three witneſſes. Of how much ſorer puniſhment, ſuppoſe ye ſhall he be thought worthy, who hath troden under foot the Son of God, and hath counted the blood of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, wherewith he was ſanctified, an unholy thing, and hath done deſpite unto the Spirit of Grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now foraſmuch as where God hath abſolutely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to doe all for men which is any waies neceſſary to be done, to bring them to an end; there remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not any thing to be done by them for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: and that not only all danger, but the very leaſt ſuppoſition of miſcarriage, or poſſibility of failing thereof, is thereby wholly taken away: ſo neither can there reaſonably be any thing required of them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, or any danger of falling be juſtly ſuggeſted unto them; (the power and truth of God being thereby di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly impeached of impotency and falſhood) and therefore ſeeing that the Apoſtle (who in all ſuch things which dependeth altogether for their accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment, upon the faith and omnipotency of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, as the reſurrection of the dead, and the reward
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:119970:60"/>
of Faith, with Chriſt in the world to come inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth men (according to the example of <hi>Abraham, Rom.</hi> 4.) not to ſtagger at the promiſe of God through un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, but againſt hope to believe in hope, to be ſtrong in faith, giving glory to God, being fully perſwaded that whatſoever (in that nature) he hath promiſed, he is able, and will bring it to paſſe, and that neither death nor life, nor Angels, nor principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor heighth, nor depth, nor any other creature, ſhall be able to prevent or hinder the ſame) doth notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this covenant (or promiſe) of God made unto the <hi>Hebrews</hi> (to put his Lawes in their hearts, and write them in their mindes, &amp;c.) ſo earneſtly exhort them to draw near unto God, in purity of heart, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and converſation verſe, 22, to hold faſt the profeſſion of their faith without wavering, verſe 23, and for that end not to forſake the aſſembling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together: but to exhort, and provoke one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unto love, and to good workes, verſ. 24, 25. To looke diligently that no man fail (or fall from the Grace) of God, chap. 12.15. And leaſt there be in any of them a heart of unbelief (hardened through the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfulnes of ſin) in departing from the living God, chap. 2.12, 13.</p>
               <p>And all this from the ground and conſideration of the danger of ſinning wilfully againſt the truth, verſe 26, and falling into the hands of God by trampling his Son under their feet, and counting his bloud (the bloud of the Covenant given unto them, rehearſed in verſe 16, 17.) whereby they were ſanctified an unholy thing, and doing deſpite unto the Spirit, verſe 29, 30. (which witneſſed and confirmed him unto them to be
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119970:60"/>
the Son of God, and that the principles of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>(viz.)</hi> repentance from dead workes, &amp;c. chapter 1. and chapter 6.1. with chapter 2.3, 4. were of God,) muſt of neceſſity argue unto us, That neither he nor yet the <hi>Hebrews</hi> themſelves, did under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this Covenant (as now ordinarily it is taken) or as in this Objection it is urged: For if they had then, doubtles he would not (having no reaſon for the ſame) have exhorted and cautioned them in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but contrariwiſe would have encouraged them, wholly to have reſted themſelves upon the faith and power of God, engaged unto them to do for them, and work in them whatſoever was neceſſary to their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; to prevent all ſuch things that might any waies poſſibly hinder them thereof, nor would they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ever have regarded any thing, that he ſhould have ſpoken unto them to the contrary, any more then if he ſhould have exhorted them after death, to raiſe themſelves from thence, upon the danger of periſhing for ever and ever in the Grave. Which ſhall ſerve for anſwer to this Objection.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:119970:61"/>
               <head>The Concluſion.</head>
               <p>THe conſideration of this diſcourſe, may ſerve. Firſt, as a means to remove out of all mens mindes, all prejudiciall and evil thoughts, as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the decrees, and precepts of Almighty God: It having been ſhewed, That in his Election he reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the perſons of any, nor prefereth one man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another therein: but extendeth and vouchſafeth the ſame freely and indifferently to every one who doth not voluntarily, knowingly, and of malicious wickednes debar themſelves thereof: his decree of Reprobation being grounded only upon the known, wilfull, and ſtubborn diſobedience againſt his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and means of Grace uſed and vouchſafed for their repentance, and reformation, <hi>Ierem.</hi> 6.30. with the 28, 29. And his Commandments having been ſhewed not to be grievous, but eaſie and light, for every man to obſerve and practice.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It may ſerve to admoniſh every man to take heed and beware of all kinde of diſobedience againſt God, and that they doe not approve or allow them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in any or the leaſt thing which they know to be diſpleaſing unto him, either forth of a conceit of their Election, or of an opinion of impoſſibility of falling away totally, and finally, forth of his love and favour, ſeeing it appeareth that he only chooſeth unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the man that is godly, the rich in faith. And that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119970:61"/>
he will not juſtifie the righteous, in the day that he turneth away from his unrighteouſnes, to commit iniquity, nor neceſſarily prevent him therein: nor will know the works of iniquity in the day of Account.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It may alſo adminiſter ſound comfort and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation to all ſimple hearted, ſincere and godly affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons, againſt all their ſcruples, fears, doubts, and jealouſies, as concerning their ignorances, weakneſſes, and infirmities, wherewith their mindes are ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perplexed; It having been ſhewed that God will never lay any of theſe things to their charge, or any whit the leſſe eſteem of them, by reaſon thereof: but doth and will alwaies behold and judge of them (through the riches of his grace in Jeſus Chriſt) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the integrity, purpoſe of heart, and ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of affection, which he obſerveth in them towards his name.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And laſtly, The conſideration hereof, doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo abundantly ſerve to beget in all men an unfeigned love, and obedience towards God. I will love the Lord (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) becauſe he hath heard my voice, <hi>&amp;c. Pſal.</hi> 116.1. And being but advanced, from the ſheepfold to an earthly Crown, and receiving a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe for the continuance thereof to his houſe, hath his heart thereby exceedingly filled with affection towards him; how much more then may the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his goodnes (before expreſſed) in advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing us, not from a ſheep-fold, but from death it ſelf, the fold of Satan, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2.14. Nor to a terreſtial and corruptible crown, but to a glorious eſtate of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality (even when we were his enemies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8, 10. and neither asked nor deſired any ſuch thing of him)
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:119970:62"/>
ſerve to kindle and inflame our hearts with an unfain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed love and ſincere affecton towards him; eſpecially if we conſider what an heavenly City, immortal crown, and weight of Glory he hath therein prepared to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon us for an inheritance and crown of reward, even for that love, ſervice and obedience, which of bounden duty we owe unto him. The conſideration of this Grace, cauſed S. <hi>John</hi> to love God, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.19. with the 9, 10. chap. 3.16. And conſtrained <hi>Paul</hi> to the obedience of him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14, 15.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:119970:62"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>BEcauſe I would not be miſtaken in my meaning, concerning that which I have ſpoken in the favour of ignorance; I thought it neceſſary, more clearly to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover; That my intention therein is not to patronize any mans voluntary and wilfull ignorance, (ſuch as that mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by S. <hi>Peter</hi> in his <hi>2</hi> Epiſt. chap <hi>3.4, 5.</hi> or that of the <hi>Jews</hi> diſcovered in <hi>John 9.9.</hi> to the end of the chapter,) For, for men to refuſe to know, becauſe they would not obey, or wilfully to oppoſe evident grounds of reaſon, and light appearing unto them, (whether forth of a hatred againſt it, or a love to walke in darkneſſe, <hi>John 3.19.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:119970:63"/>
And ſo in effect to ſay unto God, Depart from us for we deſire not the knowledge of thy waies, <hi>Job 21.14.</hi>) can be no more excuſable then ſtubborn rebellion, and diſobedience againſt the truth, clearly known and underſtood. But the ignorance for which I plead excuſe, is that only which befalleth men, either through imbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility in nature, or want of means. For as it cannot be required of an ideot to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand reaſon, nor of a childe to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betwixt good and evill, naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity having hidden thoſe things from their eies; and no talent given to them to enable them thereunto: So neither (by the like reaſon) can the particular knowledge and faith of the Goſpel (or any thing elſe whatſoever) be required of thoſe to whom the neceſſary means thereof is not offered; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which ground Chriſt declareth: That if he had not come and ſpoken unto the <hi>Jews,</hi> and done amongſt them ſuch works which did evidently demonſtrate
<pb facs="tcp:119970:63"/>
unto them the truth and excellency of his doctrine, and that he was the Meſſias pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to come; they had not had ſin in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting either him, or it, <hi>John 15.22, 23.</hi> with the <hi>10, 27.</hi> And therefore ignorance in this nature cannot be concluded any greater ſin then <hi>Uriah</hi> his carrying of the Letter to take away his own life, <hi>2 Samuel 11.14, 15.</hi> which will never be laid to his charge.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
